<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A modest plea for an equal common-wealth against monarchy. In which the genuine nature and true interest of a free-state is briefly stated: its consistency with a national clergy, mercenary lawyers, and hereditary nobility examined; together with the expediency of an agrarian and rotation of offices asserted. Also, an apology for younger brothers, the restitution of gavil-kind, and relief of the poor. With a lift at tythes, and reformation of the lawes and universities. All accommodated to publick honour and justice, without injury to any mans propriety, and humbly tendered to the Parliament. By a lover of his country in order to the healing the divisions of the times.</title>
            <author>Sprigg, William, fl. 1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93715</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5078</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E999_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203651</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863528</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863528</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115732</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93715)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115732)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 148:E999[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A modest plea for an equal common-wealth against monarchy. In which the genuine nature and true interest of a free-state is briefly stated: its consistency with a national clergy, mercenary lawyers, and hereditary nobility examined; together with the expediency of an agrarian and rotation of offices asserted. Also, an apology for younger brothers, the restitution of gavil-kind, and relief of the poor. With a lift at tythes, and reformation of the lawes and universities. All accommodated to publick honour and justice, without injury to any mans propriety, and humbly tendered to the Parliament. By a lover of his country in order to the healing the divisions of the times.</title>
                  <author>Sprigg, William, fl. 1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 102, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Giles Calvert at the Black.spread-Eagle at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A lover of his country = William Sprigg.</note>
                  <note>With a final contents leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept. 28".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Republics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115732:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Modeſt Plea</hi>
FOR AN
Equal Common-wealth
Againſt MONARCHY. In which the Genuine Nature and true In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt
of a FREE-STATE is briefly ſtated: Its
Conſiſtency with a National Clergy, Mercenary
Lawyers, and Hereditary Nobility examined; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
with the Expediency of an Agrarian
and Rotation of Offices aſſerted. ALSO,
An Apology for Younger Brothers, the Reſtitution
of Gavil-kind, and relief of the Poor. With a lift at Tythes, and Reformation
of the Lawes and Univerſities. All accommodated to publick Honour and
Juſtice, without injury to any Mans Propriety,
and humbly tendered to the Parliament. By a Lover of his COUNTRY in order to the Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the Diviſions of the Times.</p>
            <q>In the Multitude of Counſellors there is ſafety.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the <hi>Black-ſpread-Eagle</hi> at the
Weſt End of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_Parliament">
            <pb facs="tcp:115732:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115732:2"/>
            <head>To
The Right Honourable, The High
Court of PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Supream Authority of the Three Nations.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEing moved to give in a Teſtimony againſt the moſt Epide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical
Abuſes and corrupt Intereſts of the Times, I know none
to whom with more juſtice it might be Dedicated, than your
Honours, whom the providence of God hath called to be our
Reformers, into whoſe hands God hath pleaſed to put a great price,
an opportunity of making this Nation the happieſt in the World; In
order to which, he hath alſo pav'd your way, cauſing the Hills to
melt like Wax, and the Mountains to diſſolve like Snow before you,
having ſmitten the Great ones of the Earth, and cauſed Princes to
fall at your feet, and removed whatſoever ſtood before you, or might
in the leaſt obſtruct or retard the work of Reformation: ſo that no
man can any longer ſay, <hi>There is a Lion in the way.</hi> God hath put
the Nation like wax into your hands, that you may mould and caſt it
into what Form your Honours pleaſe: We are now <hi>Raſa tabula,</hi> and
your Honours may write what you pleaſe upon us, I hope it will be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs
to the Lord, that we may for the future be truly term'd a Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Common-wealth and Royal Prieſthood unto God. It was not for
nought the Lord raiſed your Honours as from the Dead, and reſtored
you to the Adminiſtration of that Power that was ſo long detained in
unrighteouſneſs from you, without doubt God hath ſome great worke
for you. And now behold the Expectations of all men are upon you; all
the Nations of the Earth are looking to ſee what your Honours will
do, for whom God hath wrought ſo many wonders, whom God hath
Crowned with ſo many ſignal Victories, for whom God hath ſo often
<pb facs="tcp:115732:3"/>
appeared in the High Places of the Field, making bare the Arm of
his Power, and rebuking the pride of your Enemies. God hath alſo
ſent a day of Tryal, that the falſhood and Hipocriſie of many might
be diſcovered, that all corrupt intereſts and Perſons might be made
manifeſt. And they that were not of you, are gone out from among
you, they that were not ſpirited for the Great Worke of the Lord, that
(having put their hands to this Plow) looked back, and behold they
are turned to Pillars of Salt; God hath made them Monuments of
his diſple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſure, and blaſted their deſigns. But the Hearts of Gods
People are ſtill with you, and their Hands, even the Hands of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>
and of Iſrael are lifed up in your defence. Alſo God is with you,
And who then ſhall be againſt you? I need not now deſire of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,
not to build on old Foundations, I know your Honours experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
hath taught you, they will not, they cannot ſtand. Our Common-wealth
hath ſtuck long in the birth, and the Nation been caſt into
ſtrong Pangs and Throwes in bringing forth our Liberties, and it
ſeems could not be Delivered altogether without blood: But we
hope now through the dexterous midwifery of your Honours Prudence,
what hath been ſo long expected will be brought forth, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d that we and
Poſterity ſhall have cauſe to bleſs God in behalf of your Honours, as
for the Builders of our Breaches, and the Reſtorers of Pathes to dwel
in.</p>
            <p>It was not intended that this Pamphlet ſhould fawn upon your
Honours in the midſt of your Triumphs, being moſt part of it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
to the Preſs before the breaking forth of the late Rebellion
(when the Author little thought his Theſis ſhould ſo ſoon be diſputed
with ſwords points, and decided in ſo ſolemn an Appeal to Heaven)
where it hath been impriſoned till now by the injury of the Printer:
But if your Honours pleaſe to receive it into your Protection, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
the boldneſs of this addreſs to your Honours; it will oblige the
Author to ſtudy how he may better deſerve the Countenance of your
Authority, and render himſelfe more ſerviceable to your Honours, to
whom he hath in all Humility devoted himſelfe, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115732:3"/>
            <head>An Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Candid Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEing in Capacity of doing my Country no greater
ſervice, I have preſented her with a Glaſs or Mirror,
in which a candid and diſcerning eye may diſcover
ſome of the Political Errata's, or Wens that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figure
the Face, and craſe the conſtitution of her Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
which I humbly conceive proceeds chiefly from the
lameneſs and imperfection of our late Reformation, in which
though we have for a long time been ſtrugling and wreſtling
with Tyranny and Oppreſsion, yet have had our endeavours
ſeconded with little better ſucceſs then were <hi>Hercules</hi>'s that
famous Hero's incounters with the <hi>Hydra;</hi> of which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
lopp'd off one Head, there still ſprang up two; in like
manner we were willing to flatter our ſelves into a conceit,
that Tyranny had received a mortal wound by that fatal
ſtroke that took off the Kings Head, and unhorſed the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.
But experience (the Mistreſs of true wiſdome) hath
taught, it is not lopping the boughs, or cutting off the top
branch of Monarchy, that will deliver a Nation from bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage,
unleſs the Ax be laid to the root thereof, to the evil
root of bitterneſs, whence ſprings all our miſery, to the root
of every uſurping and domineering intereſt, whether in
things Civil or Divine; for otherwiſe we do but prune, dreſs
and culturate the ſtock, that it may grow the thicker, the
faſter, that it may thrive the better. A King being but one
perſon, the top and head of a Monarchick State, the taking
<pb facs="tcp:115732:4"/>
away of him is but the taking down the upper ſtory, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering
the roof of the Government, whereby it is expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
to all ſtorms and tempeſts, to the injuries of ill weather,
which is altogether unſafe and imprudent, if the reſt of the
ſtructure be deſigned to ſtand, if the whole Frabrick be not
demoliſhed. And is not this our preſent ſtate and condition?
Have we not deprived our ſelves of all the conveniencies
of Monarchy, of whatever of excellency or beauty was in it,
and retained onely the flawes and evils of it? Was it not the
grand evil of that ſtate, that it ſet up a few great Families,
and raiſed them to an extravagant and exceſsive height, by
the ruine and oppreſsion of the reſt? Were not all the Lawes
with the whole constitution of its Government, made in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
of the elder brethren and great families, while the bulk
of the people which conſiſts of younger Sons, were left to ſhift
for themſelves, and ſcramble fer a poor livelihood; and is it
not ſo ſtill? Are they not ſtill the Sons of Fortune, and their
own right hands, the Heirs of their own merits? that is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabonds
on the face of the Earth, having no lot among their
brethren, <hi>ſine nomine &amp; lare,</hi> without Houſe, Name, or
Family; and is not this a greater evil in a Free-ſtate, that
pretend to an Equal Commonwealth? Nay, may not theſe ſay,
It were well if it were with us as in the dayes of old, when by
reaſon of the Multitude of Preferments, it was as impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable
for a perſon of worth and ingenuity to miſs of employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
as how to find it; or if any one were ſo unhappy as not to
finde entertainment in neither Court nor Hierarchy, could
yet offer a repulſe, hide his head in a Monaſtery or religious
Houſe, that uſed to receive ſuch to whom the world was
moſt inhoſpitable. May not theſe ſay, was it for our interest
to put down one Court and King, to ſet them up in every
<pb facs="tcp:115732:4"/>
great Gentlemens Family? Was it for our advantage to
throw down the ancient Nobility, whoſe greatneſs was bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanced
by a jealous Monarch, to ſet up a more numerous of
a modern ſtamp, without any ballance? are they the leſs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable
for waving invidious Titles, or will they not be our
Maſters if they be our Landlords? Have we gained any
thing by throwing down of Biſhops, do not all their Lands
run into one and the ſame Channel, for inriching and ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grandizing
of elder Brethren? Nay, may not the things we
have deſtroyed witneſs againſt us, and the dayes of old re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
and expoſtulate with us? Was this our evil? was this
our crime? that we ſecured part of our Lands, in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
stock and publick revenue intailed on the Altar, for the
relief of our younger Children, from whom they are now
wreſted? Is there not as unequal a diſtribution of the wealth
and Riches of the Land as ever? Is there not as much Pride,
Covetouſneſs, Extortion and Oppreſsion now as ever? Do
not men (notwithſtanding all the light that hath dawn'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the Word, and the many Hazards and Caſualties Riches
are expoſed unto) with as great travail both of mind and
body, accumulate wrath as ever? do they not endeavour to
build their neſt as high as ever? though as <hi>Solomon</hi> hath
obſerved, they know not who ſhall come after them, whether
their own, or the Son of a ſtranger ſhall inherit them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
a wiſe man or fool ſhall be maſter over all their works; is
not this an ancient evil, and ſtill a great vanity? that men
ſhould be more brutiſh and unnatural then the worſt of bruits
to their own fleſh, and like Canibals, deſtroy the very fruit of
their own loyns, by expoſing their younger Children to miſery
and poverty, to build themſelves a great Name in the Earth,
when as they know not but that their Heirs, like thoſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:115732:5"/>
may be their greateſt Enemies inſtead of the firſt-born,
for whom they deſign their Princely Patrimonies. How
juſtly doth God often blaſt and curſe theſe great Eſtates that
are the product of ſo much partiality, Oppreſsion and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs,
and may be not alſo the Government by which
it is permitted? Certainly did we belive the Scriptures, that
it is ſo difficult a thing for a Rich Man to be ſaved, and
that poverty is a temptation to take the name of God in vain,
we ſhould not be ſo induſtrious on the one hand to bar the
doors of Heaven againſt our firſt-born, and render their
paſſage through the Gate thats ſtreight enough to all, more
difficult then a Camels through the eye of a Needle:
and on the other hand offer temptations to the reſt to do evil;
I ſay, we ſhould not make the Tables of the one become their
ſnares to wax fat, and forget God, and to tempt the other with
miſery, which not unoften miniſters as bad councel as that of
<hi>Jobs</hi> wife, <hi>to curſe God and dye?</hi> To conclude, will vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
be in any reputation, while riches are in ſuch great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem?
Oh what Iliads of evils are the off-ſpring of this
Covetouſneſs and Oppreſsion? but to proceed, after all our
great expectations, are we not ſtill in the wildern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ, inſtead
of being arrived at the Canaan of our Liberties, that good
Land we promiſed our ſelves by our Reformation? or elſe as
<hi>Samuel</hi> ſometime ſaid to <hi>Saul, What means this bleating
of Sheep and Oxen?</hi> ſo, what means the ſighing and
mourning of the people? what means thoſe harſh and
querulous notes that are continually grating in our ears; are
they not witneſſes hereof? is not every mans mouth like the
Children of Iſraels, found full of bitter complaints? Is
there not a great m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rmuring throughout the Nation? doth not
not every one cry out more then ever of the deadneſs of Trade,
<pb facs="tcp:115732:5"/>
of the hardneſs and iniquitie of the times? and is it without
cauſe? are not all Trades and Profeſsions over ſtocked? is not
knavery crept into every ſhop, &amp; fraud and deceit into all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsions?
and are not Thieves and Beggars daylie multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed,
and thoſe of none of the worſt Names and Families
throughout the Land?</p>
            <p>And have not too complaints been added, many and various
indeavours? into how many ſeveral forms and moulds of
Government have we of late been caſt? How many new ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments
have we made; of how many inſtruments and
new devices made tryals, and all to no purpoſe, into how great
pangs and what ſore travail hath the Common-wealth been
caſt, and yet not able to bring forth the deſired and expected
Reformation, we have ſo long waited for. How hath the
Nation staggered and reeled to and fro like a drunken Man?
We have ſet up and pulled down; we build, and then again
deſtroy; we go forwards and backwards, not knowing which
way to turn us, being all this while groping in the dark, not
knowing what ayleth us, or what we would have, onely we are
ſick and that unto the death.</p>
            <p>Alſo many have been the Phyſitians that have undertaken
our cure, to heal the diſtempers of our State, but have prov'd
meere Mountebancks, either their ignorance miſtaking, or
fear concealing the riſe and cauſe of our malady, and ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
very unſucceſsful in their undertakings, what ſhall we
then do? ſhall we tamper no more, but leave time to work out
Cure, to heal and make up our breaches? without doubt that
cannot be ſafe, for our diſeaſe growes upon us daylie, we are
every day worſe then other, the very ſymptomes of death and
diſſolution are hastening upon us: and though I pretend not
to be a Prophet, or the ſon of a Prophet, yet I dare venture
<pb facs="tcp:115732:6"/>
to predict, if what is ſpell'd from viſible and natural cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
may be ſo termed, that unleſs God pleaſe to raiſe ſome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
and generous ſpirits to undertake the diſcovery, and with
undaunted Reformation destroy the root of all our Evils,
we ſhall yet hear our Bells ring more changes, and instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of Government be wound up to more harſh and diſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant
Notes then any our ears have been entertained with
yet.</p>
            <p>Now to know the ſpring and ſource of our miſery, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume
we need neither conſult an Oracle, or ask Councel of a
Conjurer, and perhaps it may be leſs difficult, then ſafe to
diſcover; the Caution of <hi>Solomon</hi> being good Councel, <hi>Be
not righteous over much, neither make thy ſelfe over
wiſe, why ſhouldſt thou deſtroy thy ſelf:</hi> Whence we
may learn it is not the difficulty, but danger that obstructs
the diſcovery of many things. For who will contend with
time that is mightier, or too strong for him? So I returned
and conſidered all the Oppreſsions that are done under the
Sun, and to behold the tears of ſuch as are Oppreſſed, and
they had no comforter, and on the ſide of the Oppreſſors there
was power, but they had no Comforter. Now ſhould we ask
Council of our old Nobility, the Lawyer, the Clergy, or the
Citizen, we know what would be their advice, to face about,
return to the old conſtitution, to go back again into <hi>Aegypt,</hi>
to return to our making of brick, and ſo build up the things
we have ſo lately deſtroyed, for it was better with us then
it is now; we ſhall never find out a better conſtitution in
which all intereſts were ſo well bounded and ballanced, as the
old, faith the Ancient Nobility. Nor will any ſo well ſuit with
the genious humour of the Engliſh people, and the tenour of
their Lawes, ſaith the Lawyer, Religion and Learning ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb facs="tcp:115732:6"/>
flouriſhed ſo well as under Monarchy, nor were there
then ſo many Schiſms and Hereſies, ſaith the Divine. In the
time of the King and Court, we had far better Trading, ſaith
the Citizen; nor were we then burdened with ſo many Taxes,
ſaith the Country-man, ſo that all are willing and agreed
to face about and be as they were. And whats the reaſon of it,
but that men miſtake their intereſt, and there is an evil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
raiſed on the Land, whether we are travelling, as if it
were a Land of Confuſion and not of Peace and Liberty.
And the Spies have done ill offices, which hath occaſioned
this brief Map or Deſcription of a Common-wealth, or the
preſenting theſe few bunches of Grapes, that you may have
a taste of what Liberty may be expected in the Canaan to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
which we are ſetting our faces.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore ſtand ſtill and ſee the ſalvation of God,
and not murmur againſt his providences that have ſo long
detained us in the wilderneſs; but follow the Captains and
Leaders that firſt lead us out of Egypt, and are now reſtored
to put us in poſſeſsion of what we have ſo long expected, if we
do not through unbelief render our ſelves unworthy to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:115732:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115732:7"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Author of theſe Diſcourſes living where the Keyes of
the Preſs hang at their Girdles, who had rather ſtifle than
in the leſt be acceſſary to the birth of any thing of this nature:
was neceſſitated to make uſe of one at too great a diſtance for
his inſpection, and therefore to truſt wholly to the courteſie of
the Printer, by whoſe negligence the following Errata's have
been ſuffered in many places, to ſteal away the ſenſe of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe;
there being many other ſmaller lapſes through miſpoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
and the like, together with the Errata's of three or four of
the laſt ſheets, that the Author not having an opportunity of
peruſing, muſt be ſubmitted to the Readers judgement or
Candor, to be either corrected or forgiven.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Epiſtle to the Reader,</label>PAge 1. l 23. r. Cultivate f. Culturate. p. 2. l. 28. r. after f. offer. p. 3. l. 19.
r. world f. word, and l. 22. r. wealth f. wrath. p. 5. l. 17. r. him, f. time. l. 27.
r. then, then. l. 30. the Genius and humour.</p>
            <p>PAge 6. line 13. for that Olygarchy, read Oligarchy that &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 7. <hi>l.</hi> 21. <hi>f.</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualities,
<hi>r.</hi> capacities. <hi>p.</hi> 9. <hi>l.</hi> 26. <hi>f.</hi> ſtabi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity, <hi>r.</hi> ſubtlety. <hi>p.</hi> 16. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>f.</hi> pricks
r. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kes. <hi>p.</hi> 22 <hi>l.</hi> 28. of thoſe &amp;c. <hi>r.</hi> to thoſe. <hi>p.</hi> 44. <hi>l.</hi> 16. limit, <hi>r.</hi> remit. <hi>p.</hi> 47.
<hi>l.</hi> 4. humane, <hi>r.</hi> humour. <hi>p.</hi> 49. <hi>l.</hi> 9. learned, <hi>r.</hi> leavened. <hi>p.</hi> 50. <hi>l.</hi> 23. ſtated,
<hi>r.</hi> elated. <hi>p.</hi> 52. <hi>l.</hi> 8. curbed, <hi>r.</hi> crabbed. <hi>p.</hi> 54. <hi>l.</hi> 30. concluſion, <hi>r.</hi> confuſion. <hi>p.</hi>
58. <hi>l.</hi> 11. their <hi>r.</hi> either imprudence &amp;c <hi>p</hi> 58. <hi>l.</hi> 1. ſtrain, <hi>r.</hi> theame. <hi>p.</hi> 61. <hi>l.</hi> 4.
burnings, <hi>r.</hi> turnings. <hi>p.</hi> 62. <hi>l.</hi> 2. imprudent, <hi>r.</hi> impendent. <hi>p.</hi> 62. <hi>l.</hi> 26. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern,
<hi>r.</hi> conceive. <hi>p.</hi> 63. <hi>l</hi> 21. and worſe, <hi>r.</hi> divorſe. <hi>p.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6. <hi>l.</hi> 5. Oppreſſors, <hi>r.</hi>
Oppr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſions, <hi>p.</hi> 67. <hi>l.</hi> 8. moſt, <hi>r.</hi> more. <hi>p.</hi> 68. <hi>l.</hi> 8. Sons, <hi>r.</hi> Sions. <hi>p.</hi> 69. <hi>l.</hi> 2.
reſcue, <hi>r.</hi> receive, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:115732:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115732:8"/>
            <head>THE
PROEM,
CONTAINING
A PLEA for an Equal Common-wealth
or Free-State againſt
Monarchy.</head>
            <p>I Have ſometime (by what <hi>charms</hi> I know not)
been ſo ſtrongly poſſeſt with a fond opinion of
the indifferency of all forms of Government,
that I have looked on none as objects of greater
pity, then ſuch as prompted by an ignorant and
blinde zeal, have left their memories on the file of
Hiſtory, and their names regiſtred in the bloody Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricks
of <hi>Times-Calender</hi> as Martyrs of State; for as
I preſumed all Governments alike ſubject to corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
and oppreſsion, ſo I ſuppoſed none uncapable of
becoming the Conduits of Juſtice, and adminiſtring
Truth and Righteouſneſs to the people.</p>
            <p>And therefore have been apt to interpret a non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliance
with preſent power, as rather proceeding
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115732:9"/>
from ill manners, or a peeviſh kinde of moroſity, that
in ſome turbulent ill-natured ſpirits, is the infirmity, or
rather hereditary malady of their Melancholy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion,
then from any true work of Conſcience, or
Reverence (as commonly pretended) to the Sacred
Bonds of <hi>Religion;</hi> which betrayed my raſhneſs into
a fond conceit, that not onely the <hi>Male-contents</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
one <hi>Government,</hi> would be the ſame under any
other, unleſs their ambition were gratified with a ſhare
and intereſt in the adminiſtration and management
thereof; but a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, that ſuch good natures as can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
with one, will, if the <hi>Scene</hi> (chance) to change,
and the <hi>Ballance</hi> of <hi>Affairs</hi> turn, with as great readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
eſpouſe and caſt themſelves into the imbraces of
another, as acknowledging the tribute of all faithful
duty and loyal obedience juſtly due, and of right to
be paid, to whatever Power is ſo well ſledg'd, as to
extend the wing of their <hi>Protection,</hi> for a defence to
the Lives and Eſtates of all ſuch as are willing to own
and receive warmth from their <hi>Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The conſideration whereof rendred me very neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tral
in reference to State affairs, ſuppoſing Faction
and Ambition to bear greater ſway then Religion, in
by aſſing mens Propenſities, &amp; ruling their inclinations
as to things of this nature: Inſomuch, that I have been
apt to pity and commiſerate the unhappineſs of thoſe
God had been pleaſed to call up to the battlements of
Soveraignty, and placed at the Helm of Affairs; by
reaſon there never have been wanting ſuch, as on all
occaſions, are willing to malign &amp; revile their perſons,
to caſt ſhame and reproach upon their names, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115732:9"/>
the beſt of their actions as guilty of Pride and
Oppreſſion; and all this by the verdict of a Jury of
prejudicated thoughts, impannelled in their own
breaſts, and before no more equitable a Bar, then that
of their private and foreſtalled judgements; when
as my more ſimple Charity hath been apt to prompt
me to a more favourable and candid opinion.</p>
            <p>But with whatever fond apprehenſions my childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,
and days of former ignorance and vanity might
be inchanted withal: I have at length gathered this
wholeſome fruit, from the bitter root of our late
troubles and changes, of being better able to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh
between good and evil, and of having the eye
of my underſtanding opened, to a clearer diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
of that wherein the true intereſt of our liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
and felicity is wound up; ſo as no longer to make
up the Conſort of thoſe, that ſuborned by the flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
and fallacies of baſe and corrupt intereſts, call
light darkneſs, and darkneſs light; being by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience
of thoſe few years wherein we have of late
run the Gantlet of ſo many ſeveral forms of <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
Baptized</hi> into a new Belief, and made <hi>Proſelyte</hi> to
another opinion then what ignorance and prejudice
had formerly ingarriſoned my apprehenſions withal;
as having found the Strokes of one more ſmart, and
giving a deeper wound to both our ſpiritual and civil
liberties then others.</p>
            <p>And though I was never poſſeſt with an evil ſpirit
of Oppoſition, or genius of Contradicting and Snarl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
at what is preſent; but rather ſtudied at leaſt a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive,
if not an active compliance with the preſent Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115732:10"/>
as knowing there was never any Power, whoſe
Commiſſion was not paſſed, if not under the <hi>Broad-Seal</hi>
of Heavens <hi>Approbation,</hi> yet at leaſt by the <hi>Privy-Seal</hi>
of Gods permiſſive <hi>Providence;</hi> which I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
taken as a ſufficient warrant for paying the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute
of paſſive Obedience, whereſoever I received the
benefit of reciprocal Protection: Yet I cannot but
acknowledge ſome <hi>Governments</hi> more pure, refined,
and leſs prone to corruption then others; and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly,
thoſe wherein the Supreme Magiſtrate hath an
intereſt diſtinct from that of the people, muſt be moſt
apt to degenerate, and have greateſt propenſity to
Tyranny and Oppreſſion. Now whether <hi>Monarchy,</hi>
that windes up all the ſtrings in the <hi>Inſtrument</hi> of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi>
to the intereſt of a <hi>Single Perſon;</hi> that tunes
Laws, Religion, and all things, to an harmony and
compliance with the <hi>Monarchs</hi> ſingle Will, may not
juſtly be ſuſpected of this ſtrain, I leave at the Bar of
any conſiderate mans judgement to be decided.</p>
            <p>Certainly, whatever gloſs or varniſh the Courtſhip
or flatteries of <hi>Princes</hi> or their <hi>Paraſites</hi> may ſet upon
it, ſuch a <hi>Government</hi> is diametrically oppoſite to, and
inconſiſtent with the true liberty and happineſs of
any people.</p>
            <p>I remember I have read a pretty ſtrange paſſage of
one of the French Kings, that he was the moſt Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
Prince, and greateſt Tyrant that ever wore the
Crown of <hi>France.</hi> I was (I confeſs) ſometime ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
at the ſtrangeneſs of the <hi>Character;</hi> but our late
experience of one might wear the ſame livery, makes
me able, not onely to digeſt the wonder; but alſo to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115732:10"/>
give credence to this general <hi>Aphoriſm,</hi> That whatever
may be the Qualifications of any <hi>Prince,</hi> in reference
to the perſonal indowments of his minde, the title of
<hi>Good</hi> was never juſtly attributed to any <hi>King,</hi> in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
to his Office, except comparatively: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
in my apprehenſion, <hi>Elective</hi> Kingdoms have
ſmall advantage of <hi>Hereditary,</hi> by reaſon the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs
of ſuch Governments, ſeem not ſo much to
ſpring from the nature of the perſon adminiſtring, as
of the Office and Dignity, which ever lays an <hi>Iron
Yoke</hi> of Slavery and Oppreſſion on the peoples necks:
So that conſidering the vaſt expence of blood and
treaſure with which the competition of the Office
and Dignity is uſually managed, by the ſcarlet Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didates
of <hi>Crowns</hi> and <hi>Scepters,</hi> an <hi>Hereditary Monarchy</hi>
ſeems ecligible, as the leſſer evil; eſpecially, if by
ſome fundamental Conſtitution, like the <hi>Sallick</hi> Law
of <hi>France,</hi> the abſurd (though not unuſual) preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
of women and children might be cut off: For
to hang the Keys of the power Civil and Eccleſiaſtick
upon <hi>Apron-ſtrings;</hi> and to put the Scepter into a
hand, fitter to wear a Diſtaff, is to invert the order both
of God and Nature, and to ſet a Nation with its heels
upwards. And yet I know it is the opinion of ſome,
that women and children are fitteſt to make Princes,
as being of a more paſsive ſpirit; and therefore like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt
to ſteer by the advice of wiſe Council; by reaſon
they repoſe leſs ſtreſs and confidence in their own
prudence, then men, in Authority of which the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
and proſperous Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> is uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
alledged; but whether without wrong to the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115732:11"/>
more then maſculine vigour of her ſpirit, and match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
quickneſs of parts, whereby ſhe was to a wonder,
qualified for Government, and reported rather to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrip,
then come ſhort of the more noble Sex, I leave
others to judge. But ſhould we grant this aſſertion to
to have the countenance of Reaſon, and that experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
had alſo ſet to its ſeal of Conformation; its ſo
far from being of any advantage to Monarchy, by
warding off the blow uſually given by ſuch as skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh
againſt it, with their reaſons ſharpned with theſe
inconveniences, that it gives the deepeſt wound to
its reputation that could be deſired; by aſſerting, that
<hi>Oligarchy,</hi> by the general conſent of all times and
ages, hath been exploded as one of the worſt <hi>Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,</hi>
to be the beſt of <hi>Monarchies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have met with ſome, that plead much for the
<hi>Single Perſon</hi> that ſhould be onely the name, without
the thing; the office, without the power; the ſhadow
or image, without the ſubſtance; as if it were impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
for men, that are the Maſters and proprietors of
reaſon, to be knit together into civil ſociety and peace
for their own common intereſt and ſafety, without e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting
either ſome gaudy thing to humour them, or
ſome Scare-crow to fright them into obedience: Nor
do I know whoſe conveniency would be herein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted,
except the Lawyers, who (if like Packhorſes
trained up in one road) not able to change their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed
pace or ſtile, it be prudence for the Nation
to hazard a relapſe into Tyrannie, and again expoſe
their lives and liberties to the will and luſt of an Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
Povver, to ſet up a <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Oke,</hi> or <hi>Will.</hi> of <hi>Stile,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115732:11"/>
with infinite expence of blood and treaſure, by reim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing
the Yoak ſo lately caſt off, that this pack, &amp;c.
may not alter the ſtile and form of their Writs, &amp;c.
I ſay, wherefore the Nation ſhould be ſo over indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent
to a corrupt intereſt of men, rather then to regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
and reform the forms of Law, that through the
ſubtilty of this Generation, are become rather ſnares
then fences of our eſtates and proprieties, falls not
within the precincts of my apprehenſion.</p>
            <p>Should we now unbowel and trace unto its original
this Name, for which there have of late appeared ſo
many Advocates, I preſume it would be found of as
ill complexion as the word <hi>Tyrant</hi> was accounted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
the <hi>Greeks;</hi> the engliſh word <hi>King</hi> being but
the abreviate of <hi>Cunning,</hi> the uſual epithite as all men
know of Knaves; and to ſpeak the truth experience
hath made good, though never ſo great a Saint hath
ſate upon the Thone, the Divel and a Biſhop hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
ſtept into the Office: For I am not of that fond
opinion that <hi>Kings</hi> are not capable in their private e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualities
of like virtues and qualifications with other
men; but that notwithſtaanding their accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
how excellent, how bright, how orient ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
are their perſonal virtues, they ſtand on ſlippery
places; and their dignities, their intereſts, their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſites,
their flatterers are ſnares too great for them to
retain their integrity, and therefore that the Talent of
Soveraign Power is too great, too pretious to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted
or depoſited in one mans hand, though an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel,
leaſt ſo great a temptation ſhould endanger his
fall, and make him appoſtate to a Divel.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:115732:12"/>
That Kings are Gods ſcourges and given in wrath
we have the teſtimonie of Scripture: <hi>Nimrod</hi> was a
great hunter, a mighty man, a great oppreſſor, and
the firſt King or Prince we read of, the firſt that inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
the liberty of the World, that firſt uſurped Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,
and preſumed to exerciſe Dominion over
his brethren, the firſt that put a period to that Golden
Age, wherein no other then paternal Government
was known: But though thus nigh the morning of
time, God ſent his ſcourge <hi>Nimrod</hi> as a juſt plague
amongſt the other Nations of the Earth, yet the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
of God, the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the children of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi>
were a long while after free, a Free-State, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyd
their native libertys, till the time of <hi>Samuel,</hi> when
they rebelled and deſired a King like the other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
that they might be like the Heathen whom God
had caſt out, which God conſtrued no other then A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy,
and rejecting of him, then rebellion and
high treaſon againſt his own divine Majeſty, and ſaid,
<hi>They have rejected me,</hi> and then tells them what would
be the iſſue, fruit and product thereof,</p>
            <p>They ſhould give away their liberty, and be ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
to an arbitrary power, and become the ſlaves and
vaſſals of their King, who ſhould take their ſons and
their daughters to make them his ſervants, and ſend
them forth to fight his battels, that is, to be the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments
of his pride and luxury, and the champions
of his malice and ambition.</p>
            <p>And then he ſhould deſtroy their propriety, and
take away their houſes, and their vineyards and give
them to his ſervants. Thus the Spirit of God gives
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115732:12"/>
the ſame deſcription of a <hi>King,</hi> as of what we call a
<hi>Tyrant,</hi> a <hi>Nero,</hi> a <hi>Monſter,</hi> as if they were all one, and
it were eſſential to the nature of the office or dignity
to be a <hi>Beaſt of prey,</hi> a <hi>Leviathan,</hi> an oppreſſor and
devourer of the people, which charracter hath been
too eaſie to be read in the lives of moſt of the beſt
Kings, whoſe names are not taken off the file of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</p>
            <p>Now as for thoſe that would have a mock, a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit,
a limitted King, a King and no King, an empty
Title, a bare Name, <hi>vox &amp; preterea nihil,</hi> or I know
not what: They propoſe a remedy worſe then the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe;
for to divide the Soveraignty, is to lay a Scene
of blood, to ſow the ſeed of a perpetual civil war, and
intail ruine on our ſelves and poſterity; what is divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
cannot ſtand; there will ſpring up perpetual jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies,
fears and annimoſities, which will cauſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchings
on each others authority, until the one
have ſupplanted and overturned the other, this is to
inſtitute a civil war, Anarchy and confuſion, inſtead
of a well ordered Common-wealth or Politie.</p>
            <p>Having thus unmask'd the true nature of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,
which is no other then the more gentle or civil
expreſſion of Tyranny, I ſhall endeavour to obviate
ſome of the moſt plauſible and ſtrenuous arguments,
by whoſe ſtrength and ſtabillity it's endeavoured to
be obtruded, and our aſſents conciliated to the recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
thereof.</p>
            <p>One of the grand arguments whereby the betrayers
of our Liberty endeavour to decoy us into the Iron
Yoak, we have ſo lately ſhaked off, is taken from our
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115732:13"/>
long uſe and cuſtome to draw therein, which hath
made tlavery become almoſt a ſecond nature to us
and therefore endeavour to ſcare us from our liberty as
a novel and dangerous thing, as if ſervitude were more
natural to a Nation then freedom, or any cuſtome
could utterly expunge nature; I am ſure the former
cannot reflect with greater diſgrace, or more derogate
from the honour of our Nation, that we ſhould be of
ſo courſe a mettal, ſo baſe an allay, of ſo Spaniel-like-couchant,
ſlaviſh and degenerate a ſpirit, then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
doth deviate from truth; but the worthy Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates
of this cauſe, meaſure truth by the wicked Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard
of their baſe and corrupt deſigns, as they take the
altitude of all other mens ſpirits, though never ſo brave
and elevated, by the <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſtaff of their own pitiful
crowching, fawning humour.</p>
            <p>It would waſte more inke and paper then I am ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
willing or have leaſure to beſtow, ſhould I ſhew
how much the State of our Nation is altered, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
how great an unſuitableneſs we are of late travelled
unto that Government, this argument would plead
preſcription for.</p>
            <p>But of what weight or truth it is of, will eaſily appear
to any that have taken notice of that paſſage of our
modern Hiſtory of the laſt Century, which concerns
the gallant <hi>Hero</hi> Sir <hi>Philip Sidney,</hi> who though born
in that moſt unlukie juncture of time for producing
brave ſpirits, when the Nation truckled under the
Government of a woman, was yet thought worthy of
the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Crown, and had an overture in order to his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection
thereto, had not his jealous Miſtreſs prevented;
if then one born under the influences of a femal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115732:13"/>
and not of the higheſt ranke of Nobility,
was thought fit to ſway a Scepter, of how great blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy
againſt the honour of our Nation, may they be
thought guilty, who ſay the free born people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
after they have broke the more ancient <hi>Norman</hi>
Yoke, and the more modern of a latter, &amp;c. are not
fit to enjoy that liberty, that hath been the price of ſo
much blood and Treaſure: But ſhould we conceed
all the argument ſeems to begg, that our necks ate u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
to the Yoke, and we are become familiar to ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude;
ſhall we therefore willingly ſuffer our ears to
be bored to the poſts of our new Maſters doors, and
become ſlaves for ever? ſhall we court our bonds, and
glory in that which is our ſhame? ſhall we never learn
to be free, and value liberty? ſhall we never emanci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate
our ſelves and poſterity, but intaile thraledome
and ſlavery on them, alſo to all generations? For ſo
long as we draw in this Yoke, our condition is the ſame
with ſlaves; whatſoever is born unto us is a vaſſal of our
Lords; the fruit of our loyns muſt drink of the ſame cup
with us, draw in the ſame yoke, groan under the ſame
tyranny and oppreſſion we bequeath unto them; nay,
who knows but their bondage may encreaſe, like that of
<hi>Iſraels</hi> under the Son of <hi>Solomon,</hi> whoſe little finger was
heavier then his Fathers loyns; for tyrannies uſually ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperate
and wax worſe with continuance; ſhall we now
beaqueath our children liberty or bonds, freedom or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion.
If we who have had our necks worne with the
yoke, and our backs bowed down with heavy burdens, are
of a couchant ſlaviſh ſpirit, perhaps our poſterity, if born
in a freer air, and under the influences of a more benigne
Government, may prove of more generous and noble
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115732:14"/>
ſpirits, worthy of, and knowing how to prize their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.
But without doubt thoſe brave and gallant ſouls, by
the Conduct of whoſe valour and prudence, we have
broke the Iron yoke of arbitrary and exorbitant power,
and by the good providence of God, redeemed the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity
of our Nation, from the unrighteous bonds of its
wicked oppreſſors, are worthy of, and know how to
prize and improve what hath been purchaſed with ſo
much ſweat and oyl, and will not in the end ſell their
birth-right for a meſs of pottage, but leave an off ſpring,
heirs of their own valour and gallantry, that will with
the utmoſt perril of their lives and fortunes, defend and
preſerve what the labours of their anceſtors hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed,
with ſore travail both of mind and body, and ſo
tranſmit it intire to their poſterity, through many genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
till the conſummation of all things, and that time
ſhall be no more.</p>
            <p>But for a farther and more ſatisfactory Anſwer, to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
this Argument, we may conſider how the Scene is
changed, and Ballance of lands altered ſince theſe laſt
Centuries, and by reaſon thereof, with howgreat diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty
Monarchy hath made good its ground ſince <hi>Henry</hi>
the 8<hi rend="sup">t</hi>h's days, in which it began firſt to decline, and
hath ever ſince been poſting to its period.</p>
            <p>For that wilful Prince, by alienating the Church Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues,
quite altered the ballance of Lands that was the
Baſis of his Government, and thereby did that ſervice
unawares that pull'd up the ſtake of Monarchy. For the
Church (which with all its preferments, was at the Kings
devotion and ſole diſpoſe) did at that time poſſeſs a third
part of the Lands and wealth of the whole Nation:
Which being afterwards ſold, and coming into the hands
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115732:14"/>
of private men, ſet up many thouſands of families that
had no dependency on the Crown. Since which time, the
number of Freeholders being much encreaſed, the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
hath had a natural and ſtrong vergency towards a
Commonwealth; which hath been much diſcovered in
the ſpirit and complexion of our Parliaments, of which
the houſe of Commons (heretofore an inconſiderable
Truckling kinde of Court, that was onely ſummoned
for the Prince to milk their purſes, and let the people
blood in the ſilver vain) grew now more peremptory, and
began to give check to their Princes Exorbitances, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much
that Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was put to her Courtſhip to
retain them in allegiance, as afterwards King <hi>James</hi> to a
thouſand ſhifts and juggles, who notwithſtanding all his
King-craft and cunning in which he ſo much gloried and
boaſted himſelf, ſo great a Maſter was ſcarce able with
much jugling and diſſimulation to divert the Storm from
falling on his own head, which afterward rain'd ſo much
blood and vengeance on his Son and Poſterity, to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
ruine and confuſion of his Family.</p>
            <p>To conclude therefore this particular, it being a Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ime
of truth, plac'd beyond all hazard of Contradiction,
That no Government can be fixed in this Nation, but
according to the Ballance of Land. That Prince that
is not able neither by his own nor the Publique Revenue
in ſome meaſure to counterpoiſe, if not ore-ballance the
greater part of the people, muſt neceſſarily be <hi>Tenant at
Will</hi> for the Crown he wears: For they that are the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors
of the Land and Wealth of any Nation, will
with caſe be able by the <hi>Magnetiſme</hi> to draw the greateſt
number of Abettors to their ſide, and ſo to guild ore
their pretenſions as to render them currant with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115732:15"/>
and ſo in the end, give Law to the reſt of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren:
Therefore where there is one Proprietor or Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord
as in <hi>Turky,</hi> there is abſolute Monarchy; where a
few, Ariſtocracy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſince the Crown-Lands and Church-Lands of
this Nation are ſold, what other prop or pillar of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
is left for the Throne of a Prince to reſt upon, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
that of a Mercenary Army, lyes not within view of
my apprehenſions: and then how wholſome or ſafe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
the re-eſtabliſhing of Monarchy is to this Nation, I
leave all men (that have not altogether abjur'd their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
and conſcience) to judge and determine.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe poetical if not profane flouriſhes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
Oratours and Poets, the conſtant paraſites of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
uſe to guild ore Monarchy, pretending it the moſt
natural and rational of all other Forms of Government,
and that whoſe pattern was firſt ſhown in the Mount, or
rather let down from Heaven, paralelling it with Gods
<hi>Regimen</hi> of the Univerſe, which is alledg'd as it proto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>type
or firſt <hi>Exemplar,</hi> and therefore to have ſomething
more of a divine right and character impreſs'd upon it
than any other, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe I ſay are ſuch trite, bald and ſlight reaſonings,
that they do not merit ſo much reſpect as to receive an
anſwer; for may we not as well by this looſe and allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive
way of arguing borrow a pattern from Heaven for
the <hi>Triumvirate,</hi> that <hi>Auguſtus Lepidus</hi> and <hi>Marc. Antony</hi>
ſometime impos'd on <hi>Rome.</hi> Doth it not as well qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drate
with the Sacred Trinity, by the triple Scepter of
whoſe divine providence the Empire of the world is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred,
as by theirs ſometime that of the Romans?
Will any one therefore be ſo bold as to ſay that was the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115732:15"/>
moſt natural and rational Government, and founded
by no leſs than a divine right, according to its pattern and
Archetype in the Heavens! Notwithſtanding the brand
of the blackeſt and bloodieſt Tyranny <hi>Rome</hi> ere ſaw hath
been ſet thereon, by the univerſal conſent of all Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians.</p>
            <p>Or may we not conſidering the pride, ambition, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine,
extortion, injury and oppreſsion, that uſually crowd
into the Courts of the beſt Princes, with as much or
more reaſon parallel abſolute Monarchy with that of the
<hi>Prince</hi> of Darkneſs, in which there is no trinity as in the
other, and therefore more exactly quadrate to the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luteneſs
our proud Monarchs ſo much endeavour to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</p>
            <p>I confeſs could we have a prince to whom Majeſty
might be attributed without profane <hi>Hyperboles,</hi> that
were a true Vicar or Lievtenant of God, that was not
ſubject to the paſſions and infirmities much leſs the vices
and monſtroſities of humane nature, that could neither
be impos'd on by deceit, nor abuſed by flattery, whom
the paſſions neither of fear nor affection could warp to
the leaſt declivity from what is right and honeſt, whoſe
reaſon could never be byaſſed by any private intereſt or
baſe reſpect to decline the paths of juſtice and equity,
but would mannage the reins of his power with a like
conſtancy and ſtedineſs as by the hand of providence the
helm of the Univerſe is ſteer'd: I ſhould then become
an Advocate of Monarchy, and acknowledg it to have
the impreſs of Divinity, and bear the Character and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription
of God upon it, to be the beſt and moſt abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
form of Government, and a true Copy of its Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
Original: But till ſecurity be given for ſuch a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115732:16"/>
adminiſtration, I deſire to be excuſed from being
a pander to Ambition, or the advocate to Tyranny, as
having learnt, <hi>It is not good for a man to be alone,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
on the high and ſlippery places; but <hi>in the multitude
of Councellors there is ſafety:</hi> And me thinks the very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alect
of Princes in the plural number (whatever of State
or Majeſty may be pretended) is a witneſs of, and doth
clearly ſpeak the unnaturalneſs of ſuch exorbitant mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polies
of power, and that though they act in a ſingle ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity,
are willing to ſpeak like a Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>Moſt of the other arguments of which the advocates
of tyranny make uſe, are drawn from the pretended ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
of that Government, above and beyond others
in reſpect of ſecreſie, celerity, unanimity and the like,
which though conveniencies, yet being far too light to
counterpoſe and ballance the other incommodities, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
with the great charge and exciſe they are rated at,
require no other anſwer, nor ſhall I waſt more time and
ink upon them: Yet how theſe conveniencies may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
in, we have an expedient propounded by M. <hi>Harring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi>
according to the example of the Roman Common-wealth,
by erecting a dictatorian power, if the ſtate of
affairs at any time ſo require.</p>
            <p>Having thus paſſed the pricks of the ſharpeſt arguments,
that are uſually raiſed in defence of the odd thing called a
ſingle perſon, I ſhall only ſpeak a word or two to that is
founded on the ſingle command, That in times of war
and eminent danger, when the gates of <hi>Janus</hi> Temple
are ſet open, is committed to one man, it being a recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
maxime, that reaſon hath always conceded an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
to the abſolute juriſdiction of a ſingle perſon in
the field, preſcribing to that end but one General to an
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115732:16"/>
Army, for fear of diviſions upon contrary counſels and
commands.</p>
            <p>To which may be replied, notwithſtanding Generals
are not taken upon truſt, as Kings in ſucceſſive Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies,
but upon the teſt of experience, and proved ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency
manifeſted in former ſervices; yet if it ſeem expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient
to the Common-wealth, there may be a rotation
in that office as well as others, as was anciently in the
Roman <hi>Republique,</hi> whoſe Armies were led forth by
their annual ſucceſſive Conſuls, and that with great ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs
and victory.</p>
            <p>But the Expedient our preſent Parliament hath found
out by Commiſſion, doth ſo fully anſwer this objection,
that I need ſay no more unto it; for without doubt, it
is the Intereſt of a Free-ſtate to have all the people ſo
trained up in Military Diſcipline and made familiar with
Arms, that he may not be thought arriv'd at the juſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments
of a Gentleman, that is not able to lead
an Army into the Field, it being among the Romans no
abſurd Apoſtrophe to leave the plough tail to head an
Army or <hi>vice verſa</hi> when their Military employments
were accompliſh'd: How much then may they be
thought to fall ſhort of the accompliſhment of a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman,
that know not how to manage the Conduct of
a Troop of Horſe, as I fear too many of our Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
upon a due ſcrutiny would be found, who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
all their great pretences to be accounted <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geri</hi>
or Eſquires, are ſcarce ſtout enough to diſcharge a
piſtol, or were ever militant beyond the borders of their
Ladies Carpets.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now ſound a retreat to the further progreſs of
my pen on this Theam, leſt I ſhould ſeem too much to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115732:17"/>
triumph ore a baffled and proſtrate Enemy, it being my
deſire to uſe victory with like moderation, I deſire to
bear a Foyl, Conqueſt or Captivity: Therefore ſince by
the good providence of God, together with the gallant
Conduct of the no leſs prudent then valiant Aſſerters of
our native Rights and Liberties, we are re-inſtated in
the poſſeſſion of our Birth rights, I ſhall attempt the
diſcovery of thoſe rocks and ſhelves on which in the late
night of <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> we ſplit our Liberties, and endangered
the utter ruine and ſhipwrack of our lives and fortunes,
in the dangerous Sea of an exorbitant and unlimited
<hi>Power:</hi> and thereby ſtrike ſome ſparks of light for the
future better ſteering of the Common-wealth, in whoſe
bottom as all our lives and felicities are adventured, we
are all concern'd to endeavour its being brought to a ſafe
Port and Harbour.</p>
            <p>The work then of our preſent Pilots that ſit at the
Stern and manage the Conduct of our affairs, is to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
the Common-wealth may be ſo equally bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanc'd
as it may neither have propenſity to a ſecond re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe
into Monarchy, as of late, or <hi>Oligarchy,</hi> which is
worſe, nor yet into <hi>Anarchy,</hi> the worſt of all three: But
to ſettle a Free-ſtate upon ſuch juſt and righteous foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations
as cannot be moved, that may be a ſtrong Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire
of defence not only to our Civil Liberties, as men
from the future encroachment of Tyranny or inundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of Exorbitant Power, but alſo of ſecurity to our
Spiritual Liberties, as Chriſtians from the invaſion of
thoſe that deſire to domineer and lord it over the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences
of their Brethren: Both which ſeem ſo link'd
and twiſted to each other, that what conduces to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity
of one, hath no ſmall tendency to the eſtabliſhing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115732:17"/>
of the other alſo, and do commonly ſo inſeperably ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company
each other, that whereſoever there is a Free-ſtate
or equal Commonwealth Liberty of Conſcience is
inviolably preſerv'd together with a convenient and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offenſive
latitude in toleration of Religions, as in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
Venice, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for the better ſecuring of theſe we are to take
notice of what perſons or things are moſt inconſiſtent
with, and have greateſt enmity to, the intereſt of a Free-ſtate
or equal Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>For diſcovery of which as I know it a crime of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption
unpardonable for one ſeated in the vale of a
private condition to pretend a fairer proſpect into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt
of State, than thoſe providence hath plac'd in the
Watch-towers and on the pinacles of power: Yet by
reaſon a by-ſtander may be allow'd to diſcern ſomething
of the Game, and he that is out of play to ſhew the
ground to a Bowler, and one that ſtands below may bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
know what props the foundation reſts upon, than he
that is on the top of the Tower: And it being the duty
of every one to caſt in his mite to the vaſter treaſures of
their knowledg to whom providence hath committed
the Conduct of our Affairs, I am bold, being partly
thereto encourag'd by that great candor wherewith I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
the like tribute of zealous and faithful hearts are
already received, to tender what in my apprehenſion
may have a tendency to a future ſettlement and ſecurity.
I confeſs were we at this time bowed down under the
Government of a Monarch in whoſe Court every
Counſellour of State is to be taken on an implicite faith
to enjoy by his Princes Patent and favour a Monopolie
of Reaſon as well as Honour, and that his underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115732:18"/>
is no leſs elevated than according to the proportion
his Titles and Fortunes ſwell above the tide of other
mens: I might juſtly be accounted abſurd to offer any
thing of this nature, as knowing with what ſcorn and
contempt ſo raſh an adventure would be encountred.</p>
            <p>But in a Free-ſtate wherein the greateſt Senators are
not aſham'd to confer with the meaneſt perſons, I am
not afraid to put my ſelf into the crowd of thoſe that
make addreſſes of this nature: Wherefore to conclude
this Parentheſis and reſume the thread of our diſcourſe,
there are not as I preſume paſs two or three ſorts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
whoſe intereſts run counter to, or indeed are not
twiſted and wound up in the ſame bottom with that of a
Free-ſtate, or at leaſt in the ſpining out of a few years
might not be interwove therewith, and thoſe are the <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer,
Divine,</hi> and <hi>Hereditary Nobility,</hi> as for the <hi>Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier</hi>
and <hi>Courtier,</hi> I queſtion not but a little time would
breath out their <hi>Antipathy,</hi> and warp their affections to
a perfect complyance and cloſing with an equal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:115732:18"/>
            <head>Of the Miniſtry or Clergy.</head>
            <p>IT being the Method of Heaven for Judgment to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
with the Houſe of God, I ſhall firſt ſpeak to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation
of the publique Miniſtry, or National Clergy,
ſo far as they ſeem prompted by their intereſt, to run
counter to that of a Common-wealth; and though I
know (notwithſtanding the complexion of their Coat,
which ſeems, or at leaſt ought to promiſe greater modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion)
it is no leſs dangerous to meddle, or in the leaſt
exaſperate this generation of men, then to puddle in a
Hornets neſt, or encounter a Bear robbed of her whelps;
yet my conſcience bearing me witneſs, I have neither
mallice to their perſons, nor envy their preferments; I
ſhall not forbear to give in my teſtimonie againſt the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt
intereſt and principles wherewith they are leavened:
Where by the way, I muſt profeſs my ſelf unſatisfied of
what ground or foundation may (ſince the Jewiſh Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood
was aboliſhed) be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound in Scripture for that diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
between the Laity and Clergy, which cuſtome hath
introduced into moſt Chriſtian Common-wealths; my
zeal and charity being apt to prompt me to a like wiſh
with that of <hi>Moſes, That all the Lords people were Prophets,</hi>
or rather to think all the Lords people are holy, and to be
accounted a Royal Prieſt-hood to God: Nor can I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
my ſelf learning is ſo neceſſary a qualification for
the teaching of the Goſpel, as ſome would make us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,
having obſerved our Saviour altogether rejected
the wiſedom of man, and made not uſe of the learned
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115732:19"/>
Scribes or Doctors of the Law, but ſimple and illitterate
Fiſhermen to be the firſt Heraulds of Peace unto the
world, to proclaim good will to the Children of men,
to be the firſt Evangeliſts and Meſſengers of the glad ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings
of Salvation; and indeed the introduction of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
Rabbies into the Church of Chriſt, and blending Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity
with the learning of the Gentiles, ſeems to run
counter to the whole deſign of the Goſpel, which is by the
fooliſhneſs of preaching to confound the wiſedom of the
world. Certainly the ſword of Gods Spirit will be able
to do its work, though not mannaged by the skilful hand
of an Artiſt, or Maſter of Fence, that hath been brought
up in the Polemicks and Digladiations of humane littera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
vain Philoſophie, or Sophiſtry of the Schools.</p>
            <p>Nor do I find that the Apoſtles, and thoſe ſent forth by
Chriſt, to be the Catholique Biſhops of the whole earth,
and to teach all Nations, did aſſume unto themſelves any
diſtinction of garb, colour, or habits from the reſt of
Chriſts Flock; and I have read of ſome that were cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
in the Primitive times, or firſt Centuries, for wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
large black Cloaks; for what is this but to bring
back thoſe Jewiſh types and ſhaddows, to cloud and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure
the brightneſs of the Goſpels diſpenſation, that
were long ſince diſpelled and abrogated, by the a riſing
of the Sun of Righteouſneſs upon the world; for as one
hath lately well obſerved, What is the canonical girdle,
and formality of Doctors wearing boots, but as types
and alluſions of thoſe places, of having their loyns girt
and their feet ſhod with the preparation of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor do I read that they who were call'd to the Miniſtry
did look upon that as a writ of eaſe, or ſufficient warrant
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115732:19"/>
to quit their other particular callings, trades and vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
but that <hi>Paul</hi> wrought with his hands, that he might
not become burdenſome, and it is generally preſumed,
our Saviour wrought at his Fathers Trade; not that I
would not have thoſe that Miniſter in ſpiritual things
reap of others carnal; but that it ſeems more accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to the rule and precedent of the Goſpel, that they
ſhould be content with what voluntary contribution,
God ſhall move the peoples hearts unto, then by force
and rigour of Law exact a maintenance.</p>
            <p>And when I find the Apoſtle ſaluting the Church in
<hi>Caeſar</hi>'s family, I am prompted to wiſh, that all our Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
were Chappels unto the Lord, and that our families,
like that of <hi>Caeſar's,</hi> contained a Church within them:
I am ſure it is no new obſervation, that the greateſt heat
and zeal of Religion, hath been always found in conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles
and private meetings, which ſuggeſts unto my
thoughts no ſmall ground of ſuſpition, that our parochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
Churches, Bells, together with the whole order, pomp,
method, and formallity of our National Clergy, and
publique worſhip, ſtands upon no other foundation then
that of humane invention, which by the ſtream of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt
times, have been carried beyond the pattern and
precedent of the Primitive Ages, and become very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
and diſſonant to the exemplar Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles
left us.</p>
            <p>Nor am I ſatisfied, if the generallity of men are unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable
of receiving the truth and power of godlineſs, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
the endeavours of giving all men a tincture of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
and forcing them into the garb and livery of an
outward profeſſion, which is the great deſign of, and
plea for a National Clergy, be more acceptable unto
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115732:20"/>
God then Morality. I know under the Law, God had
a peculiar people that were pick'd and cull'd as it were
from the droſs and rubbiſh of the reſt of mankind that
were to be built up in an outward profeſſion and Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
way of publick worſhip, adorn'd with many Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,
together with much pomp, and outward ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor,
but whether Religion be not now under the Goſpel,
a more inward, refined, ſpiritual and leſs viſible thing,
I humbly ſubmit to ſerious conſideration. And if I am
herein miſtaken (for I pretend not to Infallibility) I
ſhould be thankful to any God ſhall be pleaſed to make
uſe of as inſtruments to better inform me; for I would
willingly ſee and know my errours.</p>
            <p>But if it be here objected that the Primitive times were
times of perſecution, in which the Church was as it
were under Hatches, and Chriſtianity in its Infancy,
and the Profeſſors thereof forc'd to hide themſelves in
holes of the Rocks and Caves of the earth: But now
having gain'd ground upon the world and being in better
plight, and ſince it is come up out of <hi>Egypt</hi> from the
Houſe of Bondage from under the preſſures, afflictions,
perſecutions, and burdens of its Heatheniſh Task-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,
under which it formerly groan'd, ought, according
to the example of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> be adorn'd with the ſpoil
of the Heathen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, That as the Kingdom of God comes not
with obſervation, ſo it conſiſts not in any outward pomp
and ſplendor Its ſaid the Kings Daughter (or Spouſe
of Chriſt) is All-glorious within, and by how much
the more ground Chriſtianity hath gain'd upon the
world, by ſo much the leſs need doth it now ſtand of the
Wiſdom and Learning of men to commend and propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115732:20"/>
it, then when it was to encounter with ſo great op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,
and ſuch potent Antagoniſts as under the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
Emperor it met withal. And if the truth did then
under all thoſe diſadvantages not onely make good its
ground, but ſo much gain'd upon the World when it had
few other Champions than poor Fiſher-men and illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
Mechanicks; how much leſs need it now fear brow-beating
when the power of God hath ſubdued ſo many
Nations to the knowledg and obedience of his truth,
and hath made Princes of the earth bow unto the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of his Son.</p>
            <p>Some dawnings of theſe truths began in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
to break forth upon that little Aſſembly which by
way of ſcorn is commonly called <hi>Praiſe God Bare bones
Parliament,</hi> of whom many are able to bear this teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
that they were the firſt <hi>Power</hi> of this Nation that
did moſt viſibly own Chriſt in the purity and ſimplicity
of the Goſpel: But Chriſts appearance in their meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
much like his riding to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> on an Aſs, was
ſo far from being received with <hi>Hoſanna's,</hi> that it was ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
rejected and refuſed by the <hi>Policy</hi> and wiſdom of
this Generation, which was unworthy of ſo great a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
and indeed not ripe for that purity and ſimplicity of
Reformation, that they by a Spirit of Faith ſeem'd
ſtrongly carried forth unto: Which eminently appear'd
in their ſudden ſtriking at the root of two ſuch potent
Factions as the National Clergy and the Lawyers, which
they would hardly have done had they only conſulted
with fleſh and blood, or not ſteered the Courſe of their
Counſels by ſomething beyond the Compaſs of humane
prudence. And whether the Nation is yet willing to
part with their Calves they have ſo long worſhipped, I
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115732:21"/>
know not, but I am ſure it hath pleaſed God to give them
a great diſcovery of the corruption, pride, ambition, and
flattery of this ſort of men, how willing they could be to
reap their own profit though ſown in, and ſpringing from
the ruine of the Nations liberty and felicity, how wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
they could ſell their brethren ſlaves into the hands
of Tyranny and Oppreſſion, to purchaſe to themſelves
Dominion and Lordſhip.</p>
            <p>I would not be taken for an Enemy to either the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy
or true Miniſtry, as knowing they are the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
of God, and the very light and eyes of the world;
only that which I am chiefly mov'd to witneſs againſt, is,
that unnatural divorce and ſeperation that is at this day
found between them in Chriſtian Common-wealths,
which I account no leſs contrary to the Maxime of true
policy, than the mind of God and precedent of its firſt
inſtitution: And however it came to paſs that the Civil
Magiſtrate was thus trapan'd, to have the Keys of the
Church taken from him, to be thruſt out of the Temple
as an unholy thing, to be prohibited from Miniſtring at
the Altar, and ſo the better part of the bleſſing wreſted
from him, to whom (if any more than other) it doth
chiefly appertain, and this by a company of Hirelings:
I know not, but I think I may be bold to ſay it was not
ſo in the beginning.</p>
            <p>For firſt theſe two Functions of Magiſtracy and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry
are united in their ſource and origen, <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt
the ſupreme Head of the Church, who is both King,
Prieſt, and Prophet.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Moral Law which we call the ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,
and the Judicial Laws of <hi>Moſes</hi> given by
God, ſetting aſide ſome Idioms and properties of them
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115732:21"/>
peculiarly relating to the Jewiſh Nation are the Rule and
Standard for Civil Governours to rule by, and the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of them is written in mens hearts by Nature, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed
by Chriſt. Which being the common rule of
our Obedience both towards God and Man, plead much
againſt that diſtinction of its Adminiſtrators, <hi>viz.</hi> that
of one Law there ſhould be two Miniſters, eſpecially in
ſo great a diſtinction, if not oppoſition, as is found at
this day.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The two Functions were united in the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
Patriarchs, who were Kings, Prieſts, and Prophets
in their ſeveral Tribes and Families, which continued
during the firſt Ages, and more innocent time of the
worlds Infancy, during the time of <hi>Paternal,</hi> the firſt
and beſt of all Governments, when, if ever, was that
Golden Age ſo much mention'd by our Poets, a time
when Tyranny and Oppreſſion were unknown.</p>
            <p>But after the liberty of the world was invaded by Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny,
and <hi>Eſau</hi> ſold his Birth-right for a meſs of pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,
the Power of the two Swords became parted, and
to render the purchaſe of Empire more cheap and eaſie,
the ambitious Candidates of Dominion were willing to
compound and part ſtakes, permitting others to domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neer
in things of conſcience, ſo they would hold the ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup
for their ambition to get into the ſaddle of Civil rule
and Empire, by which means the Sword and the Keys
might come firſt to be parted, and ſo found in ſeveral
hands, which hath been the cauſe of moſt of thoſe wars
and deluges of blood that have been poured forth ſince
the beginning of the world, to wit, by the claſhing of
the two Powers, Civil and Eccleſiaſtick. Now whether
after the extirpation of <hi>Paternal</hi> Government and inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115732:22"/>
of the Order of Prieſthood in <hi>Aarons</hi> family and
the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> both Swords were retained in the
ſame hand during the time of the Judges, as alſo after that
through the Jews Apoſtacy from God, Kings were anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
is diſputable: Though this is certain they were not
altogether excluded, but did ſometimes adminiſter in
ſpirituals as well as temporals; for we often find the
good Kings reading and expounding the Law unto the
people, according to the Obligation laid upon them by
the command of God, as alſo conſecrating the Temple,
and bleſſing the people, things pertaining to the Prieſtly
Office: But after the Captivity both Functions were vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly
united in the perſons of the High-prieſts, who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercis'd
the Regal as well as Sacerdotal Office, till the
coming of our Saviour.</p>
            <p>And the light of this truth notwithſtanding that night
of Ignorance and <hi>Paganiſm</hi> that covered the face of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
all the known world, was not altogether hid from
the Heathen; for during the <hi>Republique</hi> of the Romans,
the <hi>Prieſts</hi> of their Gods were choſen out of their chief
Senators, and after their Liberty was betrayed into an
Empire, the <hi>Flamen Dialis</hi> or High-prieſt of their chief
god <hi>Jupiter</hi> was the ſame with the perſon of their Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</p>
            <p>Nor ſince the extirpation of <hi>Popery</hi> hath this Doctrine
been altogether a ſtranger to the Britiſh Shoars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> was by the univerſal conſent of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
Clergy acknowledged under Chriſt the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme
Head of the Engliſh Church, together with the
Title of <hi>Defender of the Faith,</hi> which hath ever ſince
been granted (though perhaps out of modeſty not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
uſurp'd) to all the reſt of our Kings and Princes,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115732:22"/>
but with what <hi>decorum,</hi> eſpecially when a child or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
was in poſſeſſion of the Throne, I leave others to
judge: But I remember to have read, that when the
Arch-Biſhop (as I take it <hi>Abbot</hi>) had a charge put in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
him, his Judge was declared the King, to whom
he was referred to give an account, as to his immediate
ſupream in his own Order; thus civil were thoſe times
unto their Magiſtrates, whereas now they are prohibited
with a <hi>procul ite profani,</hi> under no leſs dreadful penalty
then an <hi>Anathema,</hi> to lay their unhallowed hands upon
the Ark of God, or to offer ſtrange fire unto the Lord,
as they are pleaſed to tearm all Divine Service that is not
offered in a <hi>Prieſts</hi> Cenſer. Now the veſtal fire of our
Religion, like that of old <hi>Rome,</hi> muſt be preſerved upon
the Altar of the peoples heart, by a peculiar Order of
Prieſthood, leaſt all the coals of devotion ſhould other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
be quenched amongſt us; as if it were impoſſible to
retain the Ark of Gods preſence or Religion without a
National Clergy, to be its Guardians, as if the very
Heavens of Chriſtianity were in danger to fall, did not
the ſhoulders of the Clergy bear them up, were not they
the <hi>Atlas</hi> and <hi>Pillar</hi> whereby they are ſupported; ſo
much are theſe men willing to arrogate unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>But to return from this digreſſion, ſince in the head of
all Government Chriſt, and in the firſt Copie of it, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
the Patriarchs, and in the time of the <hi>Maccabes</hi> and
in the practiſe of many Nations, both Chriſtian and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,
the Magiſtracy and Miniſtry were twiſted together,
and exerciſed by one and the ſame, I can ſee no good
reaſon why they ſhould be parted now, either in the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour
or ſubordinate Miniſters of Juſtice: Kings have
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115732:23"/>
alwaies accounted the Sacerdotal dignity as one the fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
flowers in their Crown; (and why Republiques ſhould
ſet a lower value on it, falls not within my apprehenſion)
they eſteem'd it a thing moſt perilous and unſafe, to truſt
any beſides themſelves with the abſolute and total power
of the Churches Keys, ſince thoſe that by that means get
a place in the conſciences of men, and pretend to uſe the
Sword of the Spirit, have been always able upon the
leaſt provocation, to arm themſelves with greater terror,
and quench their thirſt of revenge with deeper draughts
of blood then thoſe that were only armed with the Civil
Sword; it being no ſmall advantage upon motions of
private revenge, to ſet ſo good a gloſs upon their cauſe,
though never ſo bad, as to be able to ſuborn the terrors of
hell and conſcience, and ſo make uſe of the Millitia and
Artillery of the Almighty in their own defence: It is too
too well known how apt the ſpirit of the Clergy is like that
of <hi>Peters,</hi> to call for fire from Heaven upon the heads of
their enemies, and to hold the people in a blind fear and
expectation, that their prayers ſhall be anſwered. I am ſure
this State hath little reaſon to truſt a provoked and inra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
Clergy, who not only look upon themſelves as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured
by the late ſale of their beſt preferments, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual
excluſion from a ſhare and intereſt in the Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
power, being by Act of Parliament incapacitated of
having a ſuffrage in that high and ſupream Court; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
they uſed and ſtill expect to give Law to the reſt of the
Nation; but alſo know themſelves in little leſs then a
premunire, by driving a wiked bargain, in which our
Liberties were to have been expoſed to ſale, as the price
of redemption for their Epiſcopal Dignities.</p>
            <p>Nor indeed is our State rich enough, without reverſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115732:23"/>
the late ſales, to purchaſe their good wills (were they
deſirous ſo to do) or ever bribing them to ſo great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance,
as to become the States Oratours, or to bark
any thing but faction and ſedition againſt the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>It is not a ſmall thing will ſatiate the ambition of the
Engliſh Clergy, who many of them though taken from
the meaneſt of the people, uſually ſo much forget their
Orignal, that they think the beſt preferments below their
merits and capacities: Now what prudence it can be for
the State to keep up a diſcontented and inraged Clergy,
to be alwaies pelting from the Pulpit, balls of Wild-fire
among the people, to kindle a ſecond war and combuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
pretending they are the coals of Gods Altar, for
warming the peoples hearts with zeal for his glory; is a
maxim of policy, that moves not within the Sphere of
my intelligence.</p>
            <p>I ſhould therefore humbly propoſe, That the Tables
of ſuch <hi>Money-changers</hi> might be orverturned, and theſe
<hi>Buyers</hi> and <hi>Sellars</hi> that make Merchandize of Religion,
and turne the holy function of the Miniſtry, or Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotal
Office, into a mercenary Trade or profeſſion, into
which the meaneſt of the people (after ſeven years Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentiſhip
in the Univerſity, commonly called ſitting at
the feet of <hi>Gamaliel</hi>) are thruſt for a piece of bread, may
at length be driven out of the Temple of God: And ſince
(as we hope and believe) the time is come in which we
may expect the fulfilling of that glorious promiſe, that
<hi>Kings</hi> ſhall become nurſing Fathers, and our <hi>Princes</hi>
nurſing Mothers to the Church; that our Magiſtrates
that have been alwaies tearmed <hi>Paſtores populi,</hi> or <hi>Sheep-heards
of people,</hi> would reſume the care of feeding Chriſts
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115732:24"/>
Flock with the ſincere milk of the Word, and no longer
make uſe of journey-men and hirelings in Chriſts Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard,
or diſcharge the moſt conſiderable part of their
duty towards God and his people, by proxy, or ſuffer
themſelves who are the heads and Elders of Gods <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi>
to be ſupplanted and beguiled of their birth-right, and
by conſequence the bleſſing intailed upon it.</p>
            <p>I preſume no Chriſtian Magiſtrate is ſo ill read in the
duties of his place, as in the leaſt to doubt whether he
be no leſs obliged to teach then govern the people God's
providence hath placed him over. I bluſh to think with
how great ſhame this reflects upon that ill cuſtome, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
pride or ignorance hath introduced amongſt the
chiefeſt of our Gentry and Nobility, who entertain
Chaplains in their houſes, to diſcharge the duty of their
families by a Deputy, as if they had received this new Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle
into their Creed, that it is their duty to ſerve God by
proxy, and inſteed of wreſtling with God after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
of <hi>Jacob,</hi> that <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and being their
own Oratours at the Throne of Grace, they thought it
more acceptable to retain an Advocate or Attourney to
plead their cauſe for them, as is the corrupt and unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
cuſtome to fee Lawyers before the unjuſt tribunals
of men; and that this is no leſs effectual a means to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
our cauſe to go well in the Court of Heaven, then
to ſpeed in thoſe here upon earth.</p>
            <p>Whereas <hi>Solomon</hi> gloried more in the ſingle name of
a <hi>Preacher,</hi> then all his gilded Titles, as King of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some dawnings of this truth was ſometime manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to the late Protector (before he was inſnar'd by the
pomp, and beguiled with the honours of this world)
together with many of the chief officers of the Army,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115732:24"/>
who look'd upon it as their duty to teach and preach to
their ſeveral Regiments and Companies in which they
reaped the fruit of Gods glorious preſence, ſtrengthning
their hands in the day of battel, and crowning their heads
with wreaths of victory and triumph.</p>
            <p>And I know not why we may not expect the Miniſtry
and Religion, to thrive as well in the hands of a zealous
and pious Magiſtracy, in which both functions being
twiſted and united together, may be of mutual ornament
and ſupport to each other, as in the hands of a Mercena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
and ambitious Clergy. I am perſwaded the Church
of God will never be built with leſs noiſe and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance,
then when like the builders of the ſecond Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
they that uſe the Trovel with one hand, ſhall hold the
ſword of civil power (for puniſhment of vice) in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
And as we have had a ſuccesful experience that our
battels were beſt fought, and wars managed by a praying
Army, ſo I am perſwaded our Common-wealth would
beſt thrive and proſper in the hands of a religious and
preaching Magiſtracy.</p>
            <p>And this I could wiſh might be the Criterion and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter
of ſuch as are to be truſted with any conſiderable
Talent of Power, as the onely ſafeſt way whereby to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
both our civil and ſpiritual liberties: I mean, that
the experience and acquaintance, with the wayes and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goings
of Gods ſecret providences, both towards the
world and their own ſouls, might be the teſt and touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone
whereby the ſpirits of men might be tryed and
known as fit to be intruſted with the power of a Chriſtian
Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>For though I am not of opinion, that every Saint is
fit to have the conduct of armed Troop, or a place at, the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115732:25"/>
Helm of State affairs: Yet I think it deſirable, and to be
endeavoured, that whoſoever hath the conduct of Troops
or a place at the Helm of a Chriſtian Common-wealth,
ſhould be a Saint, and one that hath given ſo good and
ample a teſtimony thereof in the face of the world, that if
ever he prove Apoſtate, a black brand of perpetual infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
may reſt upon him in the eyes and memories of all
ſucceeding ages.</p>
            <p>The Earth is the Lords, and the fulneſs thereof, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
let not the wiſdome of this Generation, the children
of this world, who are Aliens and ſtrangers to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
think to put by the Heirs from their inheritance:
for God will not ſuffer them to be baffled, the Lord will
make good their title, and his promiſe to his Son, to
whom is given the Heathen for his inheritance, and utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
parts of the Earth for his poſſeſſion, and to whom
ſhall be gathered the ends of the Earth, not onely as to
their ſhepheard and univerſal Biſhop, but alſo as to their
King and Prince to rule over them. Now for the better
preventing any miſtake, or miſapprehenſion of what hath
been here ſpoken. I would not be underſtood to deny
Magiſtracy and Miniſtry to be diſtinct in their object and
exerciſe, the one compelling mens bodies, the other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing
and informing their minds; yea there is a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction
in Miniſtry, for there is the Miniſtry of natural
and legal righteouſneſs, and the Miniſtry of Evangelical
and ſpiritual righteouſneſs, which differ onely as Chriſts
firſt and ſecond appearance. But becauſe Magiſtracy and
Miniſtry are diſtinct, muſt they therefore be ſeparated, or
becauſe they are given and diſpenſed ſingly, as I grant
they often are; and ſome have Miniſterial gifts which are
not qualified to be Magiſtrates, may they not therefore
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115732:25"/>
where they are both concurrent in gift, be exerciſed by
one and the ſame perſon? not that I think all that are
Magiſtrates <hi>de facto,</hi> called thereto by men, have ability
to teach; but were it not fit that none ſhould be called to
Magiſtracy, as Judges or Juſtices, but ſuch as are able to
deliver to the people the mind and will of God in things
that concern civil Converſation and righteouſnſs between
man and man, which is the height of that Miniſtry in
truth, which many, yea the greateſt part of the National
Miniſtry have any skil or dexterity to manage.</p>
            <p>And leaſt I ſhould be accuſed of innovations or novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
may I not alledge the practice of our conſciencious
Judges and Juſtices, as a confirmation hereof, who in
their charge upon the Bench, and dealing with male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors
and offendors, do open the Law of God to the
Countries, and ground their judgements upon conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
thereto; and were it not well it were done more, and
that their deciſions did more reſt thereon?</p>
            <p>Or might I not here allédge the practice of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi>
who uſually made ſuch Orations as we call Sermons, I
am ſure I have the Authority of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> for it in his
<hi>Holy Common wealth, pag.</hi> 29. 7. or M <hi>Taverners</hi> preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
at St. <hi>Maries</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> before the Judges and face
of the whole Univerſity in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, being
at that time the High Sheriff of the County, which is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
notice of (as I take it) in the Book of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> but
certainly Lay-mens preaching cannot ſeem a novelty to
thoſe that have any acquaintance with Hiſtory, or our
own times, it having been allowed of by Antiquity, as
well as of more modern ages, and that in the Popiſh and
Prelatical Churches, as well as Anabaptiſts for our own
times; how many Lay, illiterate, and Mechanick perſons,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115732:26"/>
have not onely been permitted and conniv'd at, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
approved, and received the ſtamp of Authority from
our late Tryers, to enter upon paſtoral charges.</p>
            <p>And is it not then unreaſonable to deny the Magiſtrate
that is qualified for it, an intereſt in preaching, as well as
ruling, not that I would tempt the Magiſtrate to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
with his Authority in things of a ſpiritual nature,
and diſcerning, to compel men therein againſt or without
their light, or to cut aſunder with the ſecular Sword thoſe
knots upon mens judgements, which they cannot mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
effectual light to unty, or reſolve; no, as for ſuch au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorative
teaching or enforcing Doctrines of faith, by
virtue of his civil power, I am no Advocate for that;
but if he may not compel to faith, may they not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
inſtruct in faith as well as maners? yea, ought not
every man as well as the Magiſtrate, to imploy that Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
if God hath given it him? &amp; therefore leaſt I ſhould be
thought either to lay too heavy a burthen upon the ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
of the Magiſtrates, or that it is the deſign of theſe
propoſals to open a door to Atheiſm, Anarchy, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion,
by throwing down the publick ſetled Miniſtry,
the ſuppoſed Pillars of Religion, its humbly offered to
the ſerious conſideration of thoſe that are in Authority,
that if they ſhall think fit to hearken to the voyce of the
people in taking away Tythes, they would think of ſome
way, either out of Gleab Lands or other wayes of raiſing
a Revenue for the maintenance and incouragement of a
competent number of Itinerate Miniſters, to be aſſiſtant
to the Magiſtrate in viſiting ſuch dark corners of the Land,
where poor ſouls ſit as in the valley and ſhadow of Death,
and whoſe hearts God hath not yet moved to a voluntary
and cheerful contribution, to the neceſſities of ſuch as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115732:26"/>
inabled by God, and having the true ſtamp and ſeal
of divine miſſion, are willing to lay out their Tallents a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
them, that ſo through the pious care of our Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates,
they may not be neceſſitated to labour altogether
with their hands, that are faithful Labourers in Gods
Vineyard. And by reaſon that the ſpirit of God is not
limited, but moves and blowes where he liſteth, and that
we expect the powering forth of the ſpirit on all fleſh, that
every one may be permitted to have the free exerciſe of
their gifts without let or moleſtation, until that time be
come wherein we ſhall not need to teach every one his
Neighbour, and his brother, ſaying, <hi>Know the Lord;</hi> but
all ſhall know him from the higheſt to the loweſt, when
the light of the moon ſhall be as the light of the Sun, and
the light of the Sun ſeven fold, when the whole Land ſhall
become a Goſhian, a Land of Light, and the Lord ſhall
be a Sun and a ſhield unto us. As alſo that this liberty may
be inviolably preſerved, that every people that are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
and deſirous to aſſociate themſelves in brotherly
love, and the fear of God to build up one another in their
moſt holy faith under any Way or Form whatſoever, and
to chuſe their own Paſtor, either out of the gifted Laity, or
learned Clergy, according as their judgements and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences
ſhall prompt them, may have no interruption, or
be impoſed upon by either the Magiſtrate or Itinerant
Miniſtery, they keeping themſelves within the pales of
the Law and bounds of moderation and moral honeſty,
but may enjoy like <hi>Priviledges</hi> and protection with the
reſt of the free born people.</p>
            <p>And that the Magiſtrates &amp; Itenerants would rather make
it their buſineſs to rouſe and awaken ſuch poor ſouls as
ſeem wraped up in a dangerous ſleep of carnall ſecurity,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115732:27"/>
in a total neglect of all Chriſtian Duties and Ordinances,
then to judge and cenſure the Religion, Truth or ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
of any making a profeſſion of the Goſpel, to which
they alſo witneſs by the innocency of an unblameable life
and converſation. And that the Magiſtrate would be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
zealous in puniſhing and diſcountenancing all
manner of vice and prophanneſs, where and in whomſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
it ſhall be diſcovered.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of Tythes.</head>
            <p>HAving thus with great freedom disburthened my
thoughts concerning the function of the Miniſters, I
ſhal now craveleave to ſpeak aword or two, to that Grand
queſtion now in debate concerning their maintenance by
Tythes, which having for a long time been look'd upon
with an evil eye, and that not only by ſuch worldlings as
are eaten up with Covetouſneſs, and into whoſe ſouls
hath entered an eager thirſt and purſuit after riches, but
alſo ſuch whom in charity and conſcience we are bound
to believe are the people of God.</p>
            <p>And ſince for the ſpace of theſe many years,
they have from all parts of the Nation been complained
of as a great burden and grievance; and that they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
ſo fruitful an occaſion or Law-ſuits and unchriſtian
contentions, to the inriching indeed of the Lawyers more
then the Clergy: I ſay, conſidering theſe things, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
with the manner of their firſt introduction and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhment
by Law, which ſeems to have been not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
without wrong to the poor (who both by the Law
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115732:27"/>
of God and their firſt conceſſion were to ſhare therein) as
alſo injury to the propriety of the firſt owners, it being
well known that Tithes were originally the voluntary
benevolence of the people towards the relief of the poor,
together with the better ſupports of thoſe that miniſtred
in ſpirituals, and were never impropriated to the Clergy,
to the excluſion of the poor, till the darkneſs of Popery
and ſuperſtition had ore-ſpread the face of the Earth, it
being then that Kings took upon them either out of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion,
or being ſuborn'd by fear of the Popes Thunder
to make theſe Conceſſions and Donations to the Church,
to the injury and diſinheriting of the firſt proprietors.
Or if we conſider the nature of the thing it ſelfe, without
reſpect to the unjuſtneſs of their original (it being a thing
that hath not the leaſt countenance of reaſon, that men
ſhould be compelled to pay not onely beyond the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion
of the tenth part of their ſubſtance, but alſo of
their labours, that ſtrangers ſhould not onely reap where
they have not ſown, but alſo inherit the ſweat of the
poor mans brows) and that under the countenance of
law contrary to all right and equity, impoſing a kind of
ſoccage or ſlaviſh tenure by the plough upon the Nation,
whereby to hold their Lands on their Lords the Clergy)
I preſume there will be found reaſon enough why the
Parliament (whoſe duty it is, as the peoples ſtewards,
from whom as they received the Tallents of their power,
ſo ought to give an account of their ſtewardſhip, and in
all things lawful to obey their voyce as the voyce of
God, according to the command was ſometime given
<hi>Samuel,</hi> though upon a worſe occaſion, even then when
they had rejected the Lord, and deſired a King) ſhould
hearken unto this voyce of the good people of the Land,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115732:28"/>
in the aboliſhing of Tythes, that are ſo great an eye ſore
and grievance to them, which I humbly conceive might
be beſt done for the advantage of the ſtate and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of the people, if the Parliament would pleaſe to grant
their Lands, might be totally diſcharg'd thereof at a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
rate and compoſition with the State, which would
not only give incouragement for a more cheerful payment
of future taxes, as the exigencies of affairs ſhall require,
but alſo ſupply the State with a vaſt ſum of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
moneys, not onely to ſatisfie Impropriators, and pay
the Arrears of the Army, but alſo diſcharge the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
debts, and probably raiſe penſions for the neceſſary
ſupport and maintenance during life of ſuch of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
Incumbents, which if not imploy'd as Itinerantes, or
in ſome other ſervice of the State, muſt on this account be
put by their Free-holds according to Law, and therefore
in conſcience ought to be conſidered either by Penſion
or employment (as heretofore on like occaſion the
Monks) having done nothing, whereby to forfeit the
favour of the State, or their intereſts in thoſe publique
Revenues; for though (as I ſaid before) I am of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
that the firſt introduction of Tythes, or rather their
eſtabliſhment by Law, was not altogether without inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
to the firſt proprietors; yet ſince they have continu'd
ſo many ages, and that the Lands have run through ſo
many hands, and their purchaſe hereby rendered ſo much
the more eaſie: I humbly conceive with ſubmiſſion to
better judgements, that preſcription of ſo long time, hath
not onely begot a title in the preſent incumbents as Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants
for life, but alſo ſetled the Inheritance or Reverſion
(as of all other publique Revenues, ſo of theſe) in the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115732:28"/>
State. And therefore as it ſeems unreaſonable any ſhould
expect to have their Lands diſcharg'd gratis of an incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance,
that hath continu'd ſo many Centuries, nor indeed
can without injury, there being no other way as yet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered
to raiſe Moneys for ſatisfaction of either Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priators
or Incumbents; and ſhould the State give up
their title to the Reverſion freely, they muſt neceſſarily
lay the greater taxes on the Nation, for payment of the
Souldiers Arrears, &amp;c. ſo likewiſe, ſince no time can
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lead preſcription, or give a juſt title to the ſweat and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
of a Freeman, whence the profit of Tythes ſeem
rather to reſult, then to be accounted the natural increaſe
of Land; it ſeems no leſs unequitable they ſhould be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
by the State, at their rack or utmoſt value to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
but rather at a moderate or under rate, by reaſon
they may (not without reaſon) ſuppoſe, their labour gives
them in equity the beſt title, if not in the whole, yet at leaſt
to the greater ſhare of them. But ſhould the State indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
to ſell them at a full value, or continue them, either
in kind or converted into a Rent-charge upon their Lands
either to the ſame, or alienated from the Clergy to any
other uſe whatſoever: I doubt the Nation would be ſo far
from receiving ſatisfaction, that they would rather think
themſelves agriev'd, then gratified thereby. Now to how
conſiderable, or rather vaſt a ſum the compoſition for
Tithes, though at a low or undervalue, would amount un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,
may be eaſily calculated by Dr. <hi>Bradly</hi>'s preſent to
<hi>Caeſar.</hi> For if the very improvement of firſt fruits and
tenths, according to the preſent value of livings, would
have yeilded <hi>Caeſar</hi> 100000 in hand, and 50000 pounds
<hi>per annum,</hi> as he pretends to evince in his ſaid Book Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115732:29"/>
to the Late Protector; how much more magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent
a preſent would the ſale of Tythes afford the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
for the above mentioned publique uſes, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>An humble Motion in behalfe of
the Poor.</head>
            <p>IF the State ſhall think fit to take away Tithes, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
conceive they may gain an opportunity (by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexing
Gleab Lands to certain Work-houſes erected and
ſcituated at convenient diſtances) of raiſing a ſtock, and
employing ſuch, as by reaſon of poverty, are not able
to ſet their induſtry on work, that ſo none may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
to eat the bread of idleneſs, nor the voyce of the
poor and needy be any longer heard in the Land; which
if prudently managed, and with that thrift and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
I humbly ſuppoſe they might, there would be lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
cauſe of terming it a robbing <hi>Peter</hi> to pay <hi>Paul,</hi> by
reaſon they might yearly pay ſo round a Rent to the State
toward the maintenance of an Itinerant Miniſtry; that
the Lands thus diſpoſed of might rather, be thought
farm'd out to the beſt eaſe and advantage both of State
Miniſtry, and people, then given in <hi>Frank Almoigne.</hi> I
have often wondered that of all theſe ſtreams of bounty,
the pious charity of many well diſpoſed people have po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wred
forth, ſo little of it runs in a fit Channel, either to
ſet the Mills of induſtryon going, or to grind bread for the
empty bellies; and the rather, by reaſon the bread that is
thus caſt upon the waters, is moſt likely to return with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115732:29"/>
and that after a few, not many days; for what
is beſtow'd in promoting induſtry, is able to make grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
returns in the fruit of their labours, when as Donati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
to other uſes do often nouriſh idleneſs, and ſerve on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to maintain Pride and Luxury. I know not of what
temper other men may be, that can reliſh the pleaſures
of their plentiful and luxuriant Eſtates, when ſo many of
their own fleſh lie ſtinking in the ſtreets, and are cloth'd
with rags and miſery; I am ſure it much abates the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
of my ſmall fortunes, to ſee any one ſtand in need of
the bread I eat. Nor can I expect to be more happy
while there is a begger in our ſtreets: O that our Rulers
would at length put on the bowels of compaſſion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
the poor. I am perſwaded if a greater door of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement
were open'd to induſtry and diligence, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
would prove a more effectual means to crowd out
that Poverty and Penury, that hath ſo long dwelt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
us; we have the experiment already tryed to our
hands in our neighbouring State of <hi>Holland,</hi> a Nation that
may be a myrror of induſtry to all the world, a little ſpot
Land which did it not lie ſo low, I ſhould call a Mole hill.
I am ſure the Inhabitants may almoſt without a Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor,
be term'd the very Ants of diligence and induſtry.
A righteous man is merciful to his Beaſt, then much more
to his Brother; God feeds the Ravens, and ſhall we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
Chriſtians to ſtarve at our Gates? How many op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities
hath God put into the hands of this Nation
for the relief of its poor? How many Abbey, Biſhops,
Deans and Chapters, Kings and Malignants Lands have
been expoſed to ſale, and yet no proviſions made for
the poor, not one Work-houſe erected for ſetting the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry
of the poor on work. Certainly the deaſneſs of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115732:30"/>
this uncharitable age to the cryes of the poor, is one of
the crying ſins of this Land, and which is very clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
at the Gates of Heaven, for powring down judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
and empting the Vials of Gods wrath upon us,
without doubt <hi>Englands</hi> poor, is one of <hi>Englands</hi> greateſt
crimes and black reproach.</p>
            <p>Having thus unladed my thoughts of whatever of
conſequence was upon them in order to the Miniſtry,
leaſt any good nature ſhould take offence at theſe no leſs
moderate then modeſt propoſals, and judge them of too
harſh a ſtrain, or ſcruple the removal of Land-marks, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
the inſcription of ſo great Antiquity, though perhaps
(if duly ſcan'd) would be found at firſt erected by no more
pious hands than that man of ſin, we commonly call the
Pope. I ſhall onely leave this Querie on the file of their
memories, and ſo limit them to their own thoughts for
further ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que.</hi> Whether ſince the Presbyterians, were ſelling
their younger Brother Independency, like <hi>Joſeph,</hi> into
the hands of an Egyptian Tyranny, for fear he ſhould
(according to his dream) have reigned over them: and
that perſecuted the Iſrael of God, that ſet their faces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
the promiſed Land, the Canaan of our ſpiritual
and civil Liberties, to the very brinks of the Red-ſea of
a bloody perſecution, have not juſtly forfeited their
Tythes into the hands of the State, and may not juſtly
account their lives a ranſome of the Common-wealths
Clemency, for my own part, I cannot but look upon
the Clergy in as great a premunire, for their ſo active
complyance with the ſingle Perſon in the late Apoſtacy,
as they that in <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. time, acknowledg'd the Popes Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy.
And I know not why we may not charitably
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115732:30"/>
enough ſuppoſe, that the reaſon why neither of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſities,
the reputed Schools of the Prophets (who
were ſo forward both by their Verſes and Addreſſes to
Court an Uſurpation) have made no earlier acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgements
to the preſent Power, or owned the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth,
be not, for that they (being influenc'd and
tinctur'd with the ſpirits of the old Prophets, the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal
Clergy) are in expectation of a turn in the ſcale of
affairs, and relapſe into Tyranny, cheriſhing a like fond
expectation of the Reſurrection of Monarchy, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time
a Prelatical Parſon did of the Common-Prayer,
applying thereto that ſaying of our ſaviour concernng
<hi>Lazarus, Our friend is not dead, but ſleepeth.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities.</head>
            <p>AS a neceſſary Appendix to the Reformation of the
Miniſtry, is that of the Univerſities annex'd, where
I cannot but in the firſt place take notice to how diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
a Key of Diſcipline, to the Government of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth,
they are at preſent ſtrung and tun'd, which
gives birth to no little wonder in my thoughts, that the
great zeal which in the firſt infancy of our Common-wealth
burſt forth in demoliſhing and melting down all
the Images &amp; leaſt Veſtigia's of the late King &amp; Tyranny
though but pointed on a Sign-poſt, did notwithſtanding
ſpare, and not ſo much as ſinge the leaſt hair of thoſe lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
living Idols, or Monuments of Monarchy, that in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
Colledge preſume to exerciſe, and challenge to
themſelves a far greater and more exorbitant Power,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115732:31"/>
then any of the Kings of larger Provinces; not onely
aſſuming the high Prerogative of a negative Vote in all
things, though of never ſo great conſequence, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt
and advantage of their Colledge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hereby ſetting
up their ſingle Reaſons as infallible in competition with,
and as the ſtandards by which all their fellows are to be
meaſured: But alſo arrogating Reſpect, almoſt. Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous,
requiring not onely their back-ſides, but the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
ſhadow of their Garments, (as if containing ſome
occult, if not divine quality, like thoſe of our S.) to be
reverenc'd, with little leſs then Adoration.</p>
            <p>They have alſo their Minions and Favourites, on
whom are uſually conferr'd all Offices, Priviledges, and
Emoluments, and that upon the account of as little Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
and ſlender Merits, as theirs who have been moſt
loaded with Honours, by the prodigality of the moſt
diſſolute and luxurious Princes; the ſteps being the ſame
by which Scholars aſcend into the favour and good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
of their Head, with thoſe by which Courtiers climb
into their Princes.</p>
            <p>Some by the ſilent Oratory of their countenance, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
with the mediation of the <hi>Q. R. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others by the perſwaſive Rhetorick of Arguments
well tip'd with ſilver, together with the mediation of
ſome great and powerful friends of the Candidates, by
which means is purchaſed the favour of being Regiſtred
in the Golden Legend of the little <hi>Popes</hi> memory, as a
Saint Canonized for the next office or preferment, ſhall
become vacant within the Sea of his narrow province or
jurisdiction.</p>
            <p>Others have travail'd to the Paradiſe of the good
mans favour, or the fortunate Iſlands of their prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115732:31"/>
in the more common track'd Road of paraſitical
flattery and meritorious obſequiouſneſs with, other the
like good work and Courtly accompliſhments that are
held in eſteem, and ſtudied according to the humane
fancy and complexion of the good old <hi>Hogen Mogen,</hi>
&amp;c. And hence proceed thoſe frequent ſtorms that
ariſe in Colledge Baſons, to the diſturbance of that
Peace and Tranquillity, and over-caſting with the black
Clouds of paſſion and diſcontent, that ſerenity of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
and unity that ought alwayes appear in the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maments
of ſuch Societies. So that inſtead of being (as
is is pretended, the Schools of the Prophets, or Nurſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
of Learning and Religion, they are become Schools
of Fence, and the very Cock-pits of little petit Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels,
and Bulruſh-Contentions; the very Abſtracts and
Epitomies of the more voluminous frauds, injuries, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,
and Trapanings; together with the other inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious
Arts of knavory, <hi>viz.</hi> ſupplanting, undermining,
ſlandering, back-biting, &amp;c. that were at firſt hatched
beneath, and now profeſſed and ſtudied in the Courts of
Princes.</p>
            <p>All which laudable Cuſtoms are the natural reſult and
product of that excellent knack of Government, the
Heads of Houſes pretend ſo much skill and dexterity in;
a thing much like King <hi>James</hi>'s King-Craft, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts
in fomenting and ballancing of Factions, by dividing
their fellows to the pious intent of keeping the ſcales e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
that ſo upon all occaſions of Elections, and other
the like Emergencies, it may reſt in the ſole power of
the politick Head, to turn the ballance which way ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
his gain or corrupt intereſt ſhall bias his affections,
and that without help of the leaſt grain of Merit in the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115732:32"/>
Candidate, or other Reaſon of his ſuffrage, then the
powerful Magnetiſm of a Golden Opportunity.</p>
            <p>This is the Government and Diſcipline under the
droppings of whoſe benigne influences our youth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
the firſt tinctures of their Education: theſe are the
ſubtle Arts and Myſteries of iniquity, in which a <hi>tener is
unguiculis,</hi> they are trained up.</p>
            <p>Theſe, are the places in which their minds are blur'd
with prejudice, and learned with the ill natured princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
of Tyranny and Presbytery, which by means hereof
hath of late ſo ſpread and defuſed it ſelfe like a ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
leproſie to the infection and debauching of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
part of the Nation.</p>
            <p>Theſe are thoſe corrupted and polluted Fountains, of
which whoſoever drinks is poſſeſs'd with a like Lunacy
or madneſs with that we read of the Galli or Prieſts of
<hi>Mars,</hi> who uſed to geld themſelves: In like manner they
who having had their Reaſons ſophiſticated and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched
with the charms of an Accademick Education,
and drunk deepeſt of theſe ſuppoſed wells of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg,
are apt by the operation of a no leſs wonderful kind
of frenzy, not onely to geld and deprive themſelves of
both their civil and ſpiritual liberties, but are zealous
to make all elſe Proſelytes to the like Lunacy, crying
down all for Hereticks, and worthy of no more favour
then Fire and Faggot, that will not cauſe their firſt born
to paſs through the fire unto <hi>Molech,</hi> and ſacrifice their
Liberty, dearer then a thouſand lives to the great <hi>Diana,</hi>
of whoſe ſhrines they take themſelves to be the Silver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmithes.</p>
            <p>Certainly its more then time, that the poyſoned wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
of theſe defiled and polluted Fountains that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicate
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115732:32"/>
and make drunk with madneſs and folly the
whole Nation, were either dryed up, that there may no
more clouds of diſcontent and envy thence exhale to
darken and orecaſt that ſun of proſperity, that in the
dawning of a Free-ſtate and happy Government, hath
once more after a long night of Apoſtacy and Tyranny,
diſplayed its Golden beams upon our Brittiſh Iſlands;
or rather that they were throughly purged from that lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
venome, wormwood, and Antipathy, that partly
from the nature of their Government, &amp; partly the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion
of the perſons in whoſe hands at preſent depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſited,
they have contracted againſt the Nations true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt
and felicity, together with the Noble Patrons and
Advocates thereof.</p>
            <p>Now in order to the Reformation of the Univerſities;
I ſhall onely ſtart a few <hi>Queries</hi> at preſent, having on the
Anvil of my thoughts (if theſe rude Eſſays find accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
or my indeavours ſhould receive countenance
from Authority) which as I want a foundation of merit
whereon to build an expectation, ſo am void of confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
to ſuggeſt much hopes to my ambition) a model,
which may poſſibly be offered to the light of publique
cenſure, but in the Interim ſhall crave a candid accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
of the following <hi>Queries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. Whether they that Founded our two great Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities,
ſeem not more to have conſulted the Honour,
then conveniency of the Nation; ſince if that had been
reſpected, the Colledges ſhould rather have been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed
at convenient diſtances throughout the ſeverall
Counties.</p>
            <p>2. Whether the complaint of Learned <hi>Bacon,</hi> that the
Nation was over ſtock'd, or rather burdened with too
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115732:33"/>
many free Schools and Colledges for the proportion of
its preferments, may not with greater juſtice be taken
up now ſince the ſale of the late Biſhops, Dean and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
Lands, then when the Church was in the height or
<hi>Zenith</hi> of its Pomp, Pride, and Glory.</p>
            <p>3. Whether ſince the moſt conſiderable Eccleſiaſtick
Preferments are now vaniſhed and quite abrogated, it
were not more for the peace and intereſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,
that the Univerſities (waving their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
of divine Right, and being the Schools of the
Prophets) ſhould ſtoop to a more honeſt civil notion
of Schools of Education and humane literature, for
training up the youth of the Gentry in Learning and
good manners?</p>
            <p>4 Whether the rendring of generous and noble E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation
cheap through a multitude of Accademick and
Collegiate ſmall preferments, where mean mens Sons
are tempted to a lazy kind of life, and train'd up to a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity
an expectation of greater preferments, then ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
the complexion or conſtitution of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth
can bear? Be not of dangerous conſequence to the
peace of the Nation, by over-ſtocking it with perſons
ſtated by their Education, and diſcontented for want
of employment ſutable thereto, and therefore deſirous
of change and innovations: Or more brief, Whether
it be not the Intereſt of every prudent Commonwealth,
to give incouragement and maintenance to no more of
mean fortunes, being bred up to Great and Noble un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings,
then the Commonwealth ſhall in probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
have occaſion to employ and make uſe of.</p>
            <p>5. Whether the Government of Colledges by Heads
of Houſes, be not unſutable to a Commonwealth; or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115732:33"/>
it be not inconſiſtent with the frugality of a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
State, to maintain at the vaſt expence of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck
Revenues, ſuch as are of no greater uſe to the <hi>U.</hi> or
<hi>R. P.</hi> then (as was heretofore obſerved of Biſhops)
great Braſs Andirons to Chimney corners, when as grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
Learning and ingenuity withers for want of favour
and incouragement.</p>
            <p>6. Whether the reſerving the Phyſick Garden, publick
Schools, with the Revenues thereto belonging for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance
of Profeſſors, together with ſome of the faireſt
Colledges in each Univerſity, indowed with a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable
Revenue for an ample incouragement of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent
number of able and induſtrious Tutors, for train<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
up the Gentry in humane literature, might not keep
up as handſome and creditable face of an Univerſity,
without the wrinckles of ſo many ſowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Doctors &amp; Heads
of Houſes, who ſerve only to check and brow-beat inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity?
And whether theſe with the ſingle Gymnaſiums
neceſſarily to be erected in ſome of the remoter corners
of the Land, as at <hi>Durham,</hi> and the like, might not be
of a ſufficient capacity for the receipt and accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of as many as are either fit or willing (now the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments
are gone) to go to the price of a liberal and
generous Education? and therefore as uſeful to all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents
and purpoſes of the Commonwealth, as a greater
number of Halls and Colledges, that according to the
obſervation of ſome, are meer formalities of eating
Mutton, not onely burdened with the unneceſſary charge
of Heads, Coaches, &amp;c. but alſo prolix Frier-like liſts
of Fellows whoſe moſt innocent imployment is to murder
time, and feed on the bread of idleneſs.</p>
            <p>7. Whether <hi>Chelſey,</hi> where was ſometime deſign'd a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115732:34"/>
Colledge for Polemick Divines, and the ſtudy of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies,
be not a moſt convenient place, by reaſon of
its vicinity to the City of <hi>London,</hi> the chief Theater of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
affairs, for founding an Engliſh Colledge, for refining
of our language, after the example of Cardinal <hi>Rich
lieu</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> as alſo for training up the better ſort of
our Gentries Sons in a more Generous and Noble way,
and leſs curbed ſtudyes, then are commonly, though
with little profit, taught in our other Colledges and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities,
and in which beſide thoſe handmaid Arts and
Sciences, together with the three learned Languages,
may be read the three Modern, <hi>French, Italian,</hi> and <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh,</hi>
and more eſpecially, Hiſtory, Politicks, the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil
and common Laws; together will all other the more
polite and neat ſtudies, that have greateſt tendency to
Oratory, and trayning up of States-men, that they may
be uſeful to the Commonwealth, ſerviceable in their
Generations, and a Crown and Ornament to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
            <p>8 Whether if care were taken, that all Arts and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick
exerciſes of Activity, for forming the more Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtick
port and Gentile Carriage of the Body, and that
are of tendency to the better accompliſhment and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
breeding of Gentlemen, as riding the great Horſe,
Fencing, Vaulting, Dancing, Muſick, and the like, were
introduced into ſome of our Colledges, inſtead of that
Monkiſh formality and ridiculous pedantry of our Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities,
might not be a means of bringing them into
greater Reputation with our Gentry, and prevent ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y
of their Sons running over to <hi>France,</hi> and forrain
ſhoars for Gallantry and breeding, whence they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
return like <hi>Solomons</hi> Merchants, fraught with
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115732:34"/>
nothing but a few apiſh poſtures and Peacocks feathers,
for the expence of all their gold and precious time?</p>
            <p>9. Whether the mingling of Military Exerciſes, and
uſe of Arms, together with the Gentries ſtudies, might
not better qualifie them for the ſervice of their Country,
and leſs enervate and debaſe their ſpirits for Heroick un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings,
then the common pedantick road of Accade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical
Education.</p>
            <p>10. Whether if were not a more profitable and lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable
cuſtome for Schollars in the Univerſities, to ſpeak
Latine, and compoſe their politer Exerciſes in Engliſh,
contrary to the common practiſe; ſince when they come
into the world, they have greateſt uſe of elegant Engliſh
to write, and a promptitude in familiar Latine for tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail
and converſe with ſtrangers.</p>
            <p>11. Whether a Labratory for Chymical Experiments,
together with frequent Anatomies, would not be of
more uſe and greater advantage in Colledges for making
new and farther diſcoveries into the <hi>America</hi> of nature,
and inriching the world with knowledge, then thoſe
many fruitleſs wrangling Diſputations in which Scholars
are trained up, that tend to nothing but ſtrife, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring
men factious, Moroſe, and troubleſome in the
Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>12. Whether ſuch ingenious Arts as Limning, Draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
Painting, Carving, Ingraving, making Watches,
with other Mathematical practices, might not profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
be taught at leaſure and ſpare hours by way of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation
to other ſtudies, ſuch Gentlemen as have a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
and prompt genius to ſuch kind of ingenuities, by
perſons maintained about Colledges for that end and
purpoſe?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:115732:35"/>
13. Whether the way of traffick and Mercha diſe,
together with the Arts of graſſing, planting, improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of all ſorts of grounds, with all other good hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry
and Agriculture, might not more profitably be
taught in Colledges, as parts of Occonomicks, then
thoſe many jejune and trifling Notions of <hi>Genus</hi> and <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi>
that are crowded into our Logicks, and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
hang like duſty Cobwebs in the windows of Juniors
intellects, darkning and ſophiſtcating the light of their
underſtandings, till the prudence of riper years ſweep
them away?</p>
            <p>13. Whether it each Colledge did every year ſend
out one or two of their Fellows or Tutors to travail with
ſuch of the youth, as were deſirous of that accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
whereby that help and advantage of education
might be rendered leſs chargeable, and more ſafe to
young Gentlemen, might not be advantageous to the
Commonwealth, and of great tendency to the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of Learning, by maintaining more conſtant and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act
correſpondence with forrain Parts, for bringing over
new experiments, and increaſing the light of new diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries.</p>
            <p>14. Whether the teaching of Arts and Languages to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
might not render the ſtudy of both more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
and facile, and be a more effectual method for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendiating
the long and tedious journey of Education,
then the teaching of them apart, as is the common pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe:
and therefore whether the annexing of Schools to
Colledges, were not a neceſſary expedient for avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
the concluſion of many Methods; and that the firſt
Principles of Mathematicks may he laid during the time
of infancy, that being the moſt docile and ſutable age,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115732:35"/>
and to which it is more grateful to converſe with Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
and Figures, rather then crabbed Languages, which
uſually like a Gorgons Head deter young Novices at
their firſt ſetting forth towards the Land of knowledge?</p>
            <p>15. Whether the ſtatutes and diſcipline of Colledges,
being altogether of a Monarchick Monkiſh and pedantick
ſtrain, were not fit to be repealed, eſpecially as to Oaths,
and the injurious annexing fellowſhips to ſeveral Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
ſince thereby is often opened a door of prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
to unworthy and ſcandalous perſons, while its bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
to them of better deſerts and learning; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
whether ſome general Rules might not be made and
calculated for the uſe of the whole Univerſity, by which
the Colledges might be better governed, then their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh
ſtatutes that impoſe ſo many unneceſſary and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane
Oathes, and imployments contrary to the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
or inclination of the ſtudents?</p>
            <p>16. Whether ſuch a Reformation of Schools and
Univerſities, might not render Learning more pleaſant
and acceptable to Gentlemen, and be a probable means
of ſtocking the Nation with a more able and Learned
Gentry for the ſervice of the Common-wealth, then
hertofore it hath been.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:115732:36"/>
            <head>Of the Regulation of the Lawes and
Lawyers.</head>
            <p>I Have now done with Univerſities, though much more
might have been ſaid, which I ſhall reſerve till a fitter
ſeaſon, not knowing whether the times are yet able to
hear them, or that I have not already ſaid more then is
ſutable to the Complexion of this Age: I ſhall now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
to ſpeak of the other two grand intereſt Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts
to a Free-ſtate or Commonwealth, which I take to
be the Mercenary Lawyer, and Hereditary Nobility;
both which I preſume might be taken off by a through
Reformation of the Laws, that at preſent, through the
corruption of time, look ſo much a ſquint at a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,
and are ſo exceeding propitious to Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,
and this by no greater coſt then prohibiting their
profeſſion to be any longer Mercenary, and abating thoſe
high priviledges they confer on the firſt born,</p>
            <l>In reference to which I ſhould humbly propoſe,</l>
            <p>1. That ſince Vaſſalage hath been long ſince abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
in this Nation, that ſome courſe may be thought of,
how without injury or wrong to the propriety of
Landlords, the duties and ſervices with which moſt
Lands are charged, may be taken off at a reaſonable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,
as the infamous Marks of ſervitude, and bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
of the <hi>Norman</hi> yoke and tyranny, that ſo all Lands
may be held by one tenure, the moſt free and abſolute
that can be deviſed; that ſo Lands being diſcharged of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115732:36"/>
ſuch unneceſſary cumbrances, the deciſion of all Law-ſuits and controverſies about Inheritances, may be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
more facile and eaſie to be determined by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict
and umpire of men of conſcience and prudence in the
ſeveral Counties.</p>
            <p>2. That the great priviledges of Primogeniture, by
which Families are raiſed to a height inconſiſtent with the
intereſt, and contrary to the prudence of a Free-ſtate,
not without injury and ruine to the younger Sons pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
from the ſame ſtock, may be abated and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated;
and to this end that Gavel kind which was the
ancient Cuſtome of this Iſland, before ſubjugated to
the <hi>Norman</hi> yoke (and that is yet preſerved in <hi>Kent</hi>)
may be inſtituted throughout the Nation, for the future
prevention of thoſe great Families, that by the two great
indulgence, or rather iniquity of our <hi>Norman</hi> Laws, are
raiſed to an height not to be ſupported, but by the injury
and ſuppreſſion of others, that being conſtrained to
truckle under them, are bruiſed and cruſhed by their
greatneſs.</p>
            <p>Not that I would introduce a levelling of all Eſtates
and families to the ſame proportion, which were abſurd
and ridiculous: But for keeping up a Gentry fit for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement
of the moſt important affairs of the Nation,
the elder Brother may be allowed, either according to
the Cuſtome of the Jews, a double portion, or elſe the
advantage of the perſonal eſtate, or the like, as ſhall in
the wiſdome of our Senators ſeem moſt expedient:
and here truly my compaſſion is apt to become paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate,
and with a Pen dipt in the deepeſt ſence of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,
to weep out an Apology in the behalf of the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
Sons of our Gentry, which though a digreſſion, yet
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115732:37"/>
being not altogether impertinent to our preſent ſtrain, I
ſhall make bold to inſert it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>An Apology for younger Brothers.</head>
            <p>IT hath been a long received cuſtome in this Land, or
at leaſt of as ancient date as the <hi>Norman</hi> Monarchy; that
notwithſtanding the elder Son obtains the whole inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
yet to beſtow a generous and liberal Education on
the younger: in which conſidering the circumſtances of
thoſe times, together with the complexion of their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
I find no cauſe wherefore to accuſe our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors
of their imprudence or injuſtice.</p>
            <p>For firſt, the levelling, of Eſtates, hath alwayes (and
that juſtly enough) been accounted altogether unſutable
to the Majeſty and gaudy ſplendor of Monarchical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
which hath ſometime, though falſly been ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed,
not onely the moſt abſolute and perfect form, but
that which by long experience hath been found moſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
to the Genius or humour of the Engliſh People, the
intereſt of which Government, is rather to have large
publick Revenues, with a vaſt ſtock of Preferments,
wherewith to gratifie the ambition of the more ingenious
part of the Gentry, who have nothing to rely on, ſave
what they can purchaſe in the favour of their Prince. Nor
was Antiquity herein deceived; for when the greateſt
part of the Nation, by this means reap their chief ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence
from the publick Revenues of the Commonwealth
and favour of the Prince, in whoſe ſole diſpoſe they are,
and on whom for this cauſe, they look upon as their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115732:37"/>
father, and indeed to whom they have greater obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations
then to their own Parents: there appears little
probability how the Pillars of ſuch a Government ſhould
be eaſily ſhaken, whoſe baſis is founded on the intereſt of
ſo great a part of the Nation, to defend it with the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
peril of their lives and blood. Nor have we more
reaſon to accuſe our Anceſtors of impiety, or injuſtice,
then imprudence, ſince heretofore ſo great and ample
were the publique Revenues, that a younger Son could
either in Church or State, by the wings of his own indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry
or merits, have raiſed himſelfe to as high a pitch of
honour and fairer fortunes, then thoſe of his elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
birth-right; ſo that to be the firſt-born was ſcarce a
priviledge, except to ſuch as wanted worth to advance
them. Wherefore while the Church and Court were
open with their large train of preferments to entertain
the more ingenious of the Gentries younger Sons, and
Monaſteries to intombe thoſe of a leſs Mercurial Genius,
there was little reaſon for commenceing this complaint:
for this I am compelled by the violence of truth, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs
in defence of the ancient Conſtitution of the Laws
and Government of this Nation, that whatever were
their other faults, they were not injurious to younger
Brethren, till after the ſale of Church-Lands, and the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brogating
thoſe many preferments that were their former
inheritance.</p>
            <p>This was the former ſtate of the Nation, in which if
younger Sons were debarred a ſhare in their Fathers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance,
they might receive an ample compenſation
from the Church their Mother, whoſe joynture was no
leſs then two thirds of the whole Land, ſo that they might
ſeem rather own'd as the only Children of the Common-wealth,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:115732:38"/>
and honourably maintained at the publick charge
thereof, then difinherited by the unkindneſs of the Laws.
A Generous Education was then a ſufficient portion,
which is now for want of ſutable employment become a
curſe inſtead of a bleſſing, ſerving to no other end, then
to diſcover, if not augment their miſery, ſo much
is the ſcene of things changed ſince <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. ſpoiled the
Church of her Revenues, and by conſequence theſe of
the faireſt part of their Inheritance, and yet nothing of
the rigor of the Antient Laws are herein abated towards
them. It is not my intention (God knows my heart)
to ſpeak a word in approbation of thoſe ſuperſtitious
uſes to which any Abby or Biſhops Lands were hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
imployed, but with reflection on thoſe good and
pious, to which (in the opinion of ſome) they might have
been converted.</p>
            <p>Nor is it the deſign of theſe diſcourſes to retrive Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical
promotions, or demonſtrate a neceſſity of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>building
the things we have ſo lately deſtroyed, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
to ſhow how unſafe and injurious it would be to
eſtabliſh and fix a Commonwealth upon the ruines and
tottering foundation of a decayed Monarchy; nor do
I blame the prudence of our late Reformers, that unhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
the pride of the Clergy, and putting down the
Hierarchy, they rather ſold, then reſerved in a publique
ſtock the Revenues of the Church, by reaſon it may
ſeem more ſafe for a Commonwealth to keep nothing
may incourage an invaſion of its liberty, or become the
reward of uſurpation and Tyranny, onely I could wiſh,
that ſince the Reaſon and Circumſtances of our Laws
are quite altered, we might not ſtill build on old founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
and intail the whole Land on a few Proprietors or
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:115732:38"/>
elder Brethren, to the excluſion and utter ruine of the
greateſt part of the Nation, and contrary to the intereſt
of a free State or Common-wealth. I dare not charge all
our late changes, and many burnings in the ballance of
affairs on this account, though I cannot but obſerve that
our times have rung more changes, been tuned to more
different inſtruments, and ran through ſeveral forms of
Government, than were from the time of the <hi>Norman</hi>
Conqueſt known before, to which how much the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content
and poverty of our Gentry may have contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
I know not, but <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Oppreſsion will make a
wiſe man mad.</hi> I am ſure the younger Brothers are by far
the greater number, and through Natures curteſie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
as rich in intellectual endowments, as poor in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes,
and being by the Tyranny (as affairs now ſtand)
of Law and cuſtome debarred, ſharing in their Parents
Eſtates, to which they conceive Nature equally intitles
them with their elder Brother; its no wonder if they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
to interrupt the Peace and Tranquillity of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,
ſince by the ſhakings thereof they may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably
root themſelves in fairer fortunes, then from its
peace and ſettlement, they may with reaſon expect; and
that which arms their diſcontent with fit weapons for
revenge, and renders them more formidable, is their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous
Education; for certainly its of very unſafe and
dangerous conſequence, to qualifie ſuch for great and
noble undertakings, that are Heirs to no other fortunes
then what their valours can purchaſe with the ruine of
the Commonwealths Peace and Government. Therefore
had thoſe that made the publique Revenues a prey to
their Ambition, alſo drunk up thoſe ſtreams of bounty,
by which the Schools and Univerſities are fed and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:115732:39"/>
and ſo taken away the means as well as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement
of liberal Education, they had better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted
the Peace, though not the honour of the Nation:
for ſo long as theſe are open (if not better ordered) I
doubt there will be Vipers hatched to eat through the
wombe of Government, by which they conceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
injured and debarred, both that which nature gives
them title to of their Parents, and the ancient conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of the Common-wealth in publick, Revenues which
I would not have underſtood as proceeding from any
prejudice or ill will to the Vniverſities, which I much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
and in which with thankfulneſs I acknowledge to
have received my Education, but onely to diſcover the
ſhortneſs of that policy, that taking away the Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
ſhould reward and Crown all Accademick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours,
yet never reduced the means whereby men are
qual fied for an expectation, and prompted to an am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition
of them; and indeed of a like ſtrain is moſt of our
modern policy, not skin deep, and rather to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
ſhifts and preſent evaſions of imprudent evils, then
Antidotes of ſolid prudence for either the obviating, or
healing any diſaſter or malady in the body politick.</p>
            <p>Certainly a generous Education is not proper for ſuch
as are intended for little leſs then ſlaves. It is Ignorance
is the Mother of Obedience, whereas knowledge makes
men proud and factious, eſpecially when they concern
their fortunes and employments, are not correſpondent
to the grandure of their birth and education.</p>
            <p>The younger Son is apt to think himſelf ſprung from
as Noble a ſtock, from the loyns of as good a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
as his elder Brother, and therefore cannot but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
why fortune and the Law ſhould make ſo great a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:115732:39"/>
difference between them that lay in the ſame wombe, that
are formed of the ſame lump; why Law or Cuſtome
ſhould deny them an eſtate, whom nature hath given diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion
to know how to manage it.</p>
            <p>Learning ennobles and elevates the ſoul, cauſing it to
deſpiſe and ſet light by ſmall and baſe things, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
where that flouriſhes, men are not eaſily taught to
ſubmit their necks to an Iron yoke of ſlavery; which
promps the Turkiſh prudence to extinguiſh all ſuch
lights by which men gain a proſpect or diſcovery of the
thraldom and miſery of their Condition. It would
drink more ink, and waſte more time then I, or perhaps
the Reader would willingly beſtow, to give an accompt
of all the miſchiefs and inconveninces that proceed from
the fertil wombe of this ſingle miſtake, that a generous
Education (notwithſtanding the abolition of all incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements
of Learning and ingenious Preforments) is a
ſufficient portion for a younger Brother. Wiſdome is
good with an Inheritance, but the wiſdome of the poor
man is deſpiſed. The Muſes without a Dowry are but
deſpicable Virgins, and the unnatural, though uſual and
worſe, that is at this day found between Wit and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,
renders both uſeleſs, if not pernitious to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.
I doubt not but ſhould we take a view of
things through the proſpective of ſome mens Obſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
we ſhould diſcover this in part the cauſe of that
tranquillity and ſettlement, peace and proſperity, with
which in former times this Brittiſh Iſle was Crowned; as
alſo of thoſe many ſhakings and Convulſions in which
theſe latter Ages have ſeen her caſt into: And can we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
it ſhould be otherwiſe? when (as <hi>Solomon</hi> hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved)
<hi>There is not bread to the wiſe, nor riches to men of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:115732:40"/>
underſtanding, nor yet favour to men to skill, &amp;c.</hi> which
ſeems to proceed from no other cauſe then the iniquity of
our Laws, pouring all the wrath into one Channel, and
conveying the whole Land into the hands of a few Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors
or elder brethren.</p>
            <p>I confeſs thoſe providence hath placed on high, on the
battlements of ſupream power, may if their eys are open,
and not blinded by private intereſt, command a fairer
proſpect, and diſcern farther into theſe things then ſuch
whom a meaner fortune hath left in the valley of a low
and private condition, therefore I ſhall not preſume to
inform thoſe Intelligences that turn about the Orbs of
Government; onely could wiſh there were ſuch a ſcene
of things brought forth as may give incouragement to
expect a ſettlement without a miracle.</p>
            <p>To which as things now ſtand, I cannot perſwade my
ſelfe but that the eſtabliſhing of Gavel-kind would have
no ſmall tendency; for can any thing be done more ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
to a Common-wealth? or is there any thing more
juſt and equitable, then that all the Children ſhould ſhare
in their Parents Inheritances? or indeed is there not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
an abſolute neceſſity thereof, ſince all the former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues
by which men had acceſs to Preferment are hedg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
up? is not the onely door at preſent open to a fortune,
that of the Law? which is alſo now together with all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
profeſſions ſo overſtock'd with ſtudents, and thereby
become ſo burdenſome, that the Nation will no longer
indure it. For are they not neceſſitated to deviſe dayly
new Querks and ſubtilties, whereby ſuits may be multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
to the confuſion of Eſtates and Oppreſſion of the
people; How much more honourable would it be to our
Reformation and new eſtabliſhed Government, that there
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:115732:40"/>
were a more equall and righteous diſtribution of the
things of this Earth; then that the greater part of the
Nation ſhould be put to ſhift and ſcamble for a liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,
or be neceſſitated to live on the ſins of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.
Not that I would adviſe to break down the hedge
of propriety, by a promiſcuous and injurious levelling
of Eſtates; and ſo open a gap to confuſion; no, none
but a devil would adviſe that: But why Eſtates may not
for the future deſcend regularly to the whole Off-spring
that are of the ſame bloud and family, in ſtead of one
branch thereof, I know no inconvenience in that, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
in thoſe circumſtances we are in at preſent, being
fallen into an Age ſo Eagle-cy'd and quick-ſighted, as to
diſcern ſpots in the Sun, and diſcover corruption in the
Heavens; which the duller Opticks of Antiquity judged
immaculate, and as altogether incorruptible: An Age
that dares pry into the pious frauds, and unmask the moſt
religious deceits, which the devouter ignorance of our
Anceſtors never beheld, but at a ſuperſtitious and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentiall
diſtance: An age in which the art of living or to
gain an honeſt ſubſiſtence, is grown ſo ſubtle, ſo diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult
and abſtruſe a myſtery, that few are able to maſter
it: In which the younger ſons of our Nobility and chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
Gentry, are neceſſitated to ſtoop (for want of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
employments) to low, ſervile, baſe and mechanick
employments, or do worſe, by reaſon whereof ſome Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens
have of late years been elated to that ſtrange de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
of pride and arrogance, as with ſcorn to refuſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting
any lower rank then the children of the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
to be their ſervants, or that leſſe than an Eſquire ſhould
wipe their ſhooes, ſo much hath wealth gotten the ſtart
of Birth, Education, and Virtue. How juſtly may the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:115732:41"/>
younger Children of this Nation take up that of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi>
and apply unto themſelves: <hi>There is no more remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
of the wiſe then of the fool, and the ſame happeneth
unto both; wherefore is one wiſer then another, for poverty
is the portion of them both:</hi> and may ſay, their oppreſſors
are encreaſed (like thoſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egypt</hi>) as their
numbers are multiplied. How great an encouragement
would it be to thoſe that are ingenious to have ſome
foundation whereon to build their fortunes, to have
ſomething, ſome ſtock wherewith to begin the world,
and ſet the wheel of their inventions going: How many
ingenious Gentlemen that are now cloth'd with rags and
miſery, might have raiſed themſelves to fair Eſtates, had
they had a ſtock wherewith to ſet their induſtry on work;
for can any man make brick wherewith to build them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
a fortune without any ſtraw? How many might
this have reprieved from an untimely death, who might
have been uſefull to their Countrey, and Ornaments to
the Common-wealth, had their parts and ingenuities
found due encouragement? How many brave ſparkling
Wits, that might have proved bright ſtars and ſhining
lamps both in Church and Commonwealth, have been
extinguiſht in obſcurity, for want of maintenance, the
oyle whereby their lamps ſhould have been fed and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed?</p>
            <p>What's the Reaſon ſo many of the beſt Names and
Families throughout the Realm lie ſtinking in the ſtreets
covered with rags and vermine, but that for a fond and
idle fanſie of keeping up the name and family, the whole
Inheritance is intayl'd on the firſt-born, and nothing but
poverty and miſery on all the reſt of the bloud and kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred,
as if it were leſſe diſcredit to have many beggars,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:115732:41"/>
then not to have one Gallant that is able to fly a Hawk,
and keep up the cry of Hounds belonging to the Family?
What madneſſe is it, that on the account of Primogeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
the whole Eſtate ſhould be ſwept away by one who
perhaps is fitter to wear long coats and a fools cap, then
manage an Eſtate, or hath not a grain more wit then will
juſt ſecure its being beg'd, or that elſe perhaps will ſpend
it on Whores and Sycophants, while his moſt ingenious
Brethren, are either rooſted under the ruines of ſome
ſmoaky old Cottage, or expoſed as Penſioners to be
maintained by the cold charity of a wretched miſerable
world?</p>
            <p>It was a cuſtome among the Heathen (juſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
by Chriſtians) for the Father to appoint and
deſigne ſuch of his Off-spring ſo ſoon as brought forth,
on which he was willing to beſtow the coſt of Nurture
and Education, which was performed by the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
of lifting it from the ground, on which the Midwife
had for that purpoſe ſet it, and was commonly the lot of
thoſe Nature had moſt accurately form'd, and ſeal'd
with the moſt promiſing ſignatures to vouch a future e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence:
Whereas the reſt, eſpecially ſuch as were
branded with any kinde of monſtroſity or notable defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,
were no ſooner enlarged from the dark chambers
of their Mothers Wombs, but expos'd as a prey to be
entomb'd in the bowels of wilde beaſts, before they were
capable of knowing the Authours of their injury, or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
any reſentment of their Parents inhoſpitality or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindeneſſe:
Whereas we on the other ſide take pleaſure
in a numerous offspring, and though we do not expoſe
any which is forbidden by our laws, yet commonly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
bread to all, except the eldeſt, ſending forth our yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:115732:42"/>
fry more naked and unarm'd into the world then
Bees their caſtlings, as if they could feed on the breaſts
of flowers, or glean up an Eſtate with a like facility, as
thoſe little Animals do their honey.</p>
            <p>I have often wondred at the great ſeverity of our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
Law, that mulcts the pruning away of the leaſt ſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
excreſcency of luſt with no leſſe penalty then death,
when as it denies all younger Sons, though never ſo legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timately
ſprung from a noble ſtock to ſhare or receive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
ſap there from, leſt thereby the growth of the top
branch ſhould be hindred from attaining that extravagant
height, to which by the withering and ruine of the reſt
its proud ambition might aſpire to climb; ſo that all the
mercy our Law affords theſe younger ſprouts, is only a
bare protection from the ſtroke of a more ſudden and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent
end (that might do them the kindeneſſe of putting
a quick period to their lingring pain, whoſe life is only
upheld by the bread of affliction) while they conſume
with poverty, and at length wither and dwindle away by
want or famine.</p>
            <p>Were it not far more juſt to reſtrain Marriage, or
at leaſt give check and ſet bounds to the luſt of Parents,
by ſtinting the number of their off-spring to a childe or
two, and ſealing up the fertile womb, then thus turn
that bleſſing of God, <hi>Increaſe and multiply,</hi> into the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
curſe, and <hi>viſit the iniquity of the Parents upon the
Children?</hi> Or were it not a greater act of charity, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the example of the Heathen, to expoſe or drown
theſe latter births, as we do ſuch ſupernumerary dogs <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
as would otherwiſe ore-ſtock our Commous, then thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
them like ſo many little <hi>Moſes</hi>'s in Arks of Bulruſhes
to a Sea of poverty and miſery, from whence they may
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:115732:42"/>
never expect reprieve, unleſſe ſome miraculous Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
(like <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughters) chance reſcue them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
her Court and favour? Our Law making no more
proviſion for younger Brethren then if they were to be
cloth'd like the Lillies of the field, or like <hi>Elias</hi> to expect
their food from Ravens, receiving no other comfort from
the hands of men, then what they can ſuck from the dry
breaſts of an old Proverb, that God will ſend meat
whereſoever he hath provided mouths, then which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
more true, did not the covetouſneſſe of men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
it.</p>
            <p>It was the cuſtome of our Gentry and Nobility to
clap ſuch of their flegmatick off-spring, as nature had not
made mercuriall enough to ambiate either Church or
Court preferments into ſome religious habit; and ſo
keep up the ſplendour of their Families, by pruning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
ſuch under branches for the ſervice of the Altar, as
either through their number or folly were like to lett in
poverty, and thereby become a diſparagement to the
noble ſtock, from whence they ſprang, which hath
prompted ſome to an opinion, that if in theſe more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous
Northern Climates, a kinde of Proteſtant Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries
were erected for encouragement of Chaſtity and
ſingle life, eſpecially among the poor ſort: it would
(pardoning the ſoloeciſme of the name) be more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant
to the Maxims of ſtate and true policy, then in
thoſe hotter and more barren Climates, where there is
ſo little danger of being ore-ſtock'd or burdend with peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
that on the contrary they want men for the neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
defence of their Territories: Of which we have a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent
Inſtance in <hi>Spain,</hi> whoſe Religious Houſes (did not
their blinde devotion ſo much triumph over their Policy)
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:115732:43"/>
had long ſince been buryed under their own ruines; for
there can no other account be given, why that wiſe and
prudent Nation labouring under ſo great a weight of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs,
and ſcarcity of men, to manage their wars, ſhould
tolerate ſo many hives of drones; Which ſo long as they
ſhall continue, may give good caution and ſecurity to its
Neighbouring States and Princes, to lay aſleep their fears
and jealouſies of his ever attaining that Univerſal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,
at which for ſo many centuries the lips of his
proud ambition have been thought to water: there being
little probability that his palſie hands ſhould graſpe the
Univerſe, that hath not ſtrength enough to hold that little
part thereof, he hath already faſtened on, and therefore
the Spaniſh Conqueſts may not unfitly be compar'd to
thoſe of Rivers upon the banks of their channels, looſing
as much in one place as they gain in another.</p>
            <p>But ſince Providence hath been pleaſed in mercy to
bring back our captivity, and again to caſt us into the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious
form of a Commonwealth, if Gavell-kinde
were once eſtabliſhed, we ſhall ſtand in need of no other
devices for keeping out of poverty, then the ſetting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry
on work according to the opportunities plentifull
occaſions will adminiſter in an equall Commonwealth.
But I ſhall now return to the Lawyers from whom I have
made ſo long a digreſſion: I have read that in the more
pure and leſſe ſophiſticated times of our Anceſtors, great
Eſtates have been paſſed in few words, and the convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
proved more firm and good then thoſe tedious, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix,
tautologicall Inſtruments, the knavery of latter
Ages hath introduced.</p>
            <l>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:115732:43"/>
In ſigne that this is ſooth</l>
            <l>I bite the white wax with my tooth.</l>
            <p>Or the like being the form of thoſe more ſimple and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerer
times, whereas now through the fraud of Lawyers
all things are ſo ambiguouſly pen'd, that none but a
Sphinx in their myſteries is able to underſtand or unrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle
them.</p>
            <p>The Profeſſors of which myſtery of iniquity that live
upon the ſins of the yeople, are of late grown ſo nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous,
that like Locuſts or an Egyptian plague of Cater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillars
they cover the face of our land, and are thriven to
ſuch vaſt Eſtates, that whereas heretofore the Church
and Clergy being in poſſeſſion of two thirds, of the beſt
Lands throughout the Realm, gave birth to the ſtatute of
<hi>Mortmain</hi> for ſecurity of the reſt: We may juſtly fear
unleſſe ſome prudent care be taken for prevention of their
future purchaſes, leſt this Pack, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by their Querks <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
inſtate themſelves in our Inheritances, and ingroſſe the
wealth and Revenues of the whole Nation unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have heard this ſubtle Generation were not in ſo fair
a plight, when every Term they beat upon the hoof to
<hi>London</hi> with their Satchels on their backs, and at the
Towns end proffered their Services, like Watermen at
the Thames ſide, to be retained by the Countrey Clients;
and I know not whether we may ever expect a golden
Age, or to ſee good dayes, till the intereſt of this corrupt
Generation be laid as low as any Hiſtories can produce a
preſident; which at this time muſt needs have the greateſt
countenance of juſtice that can be, they having been ſo
notoriouſly inſtrumental in betraying our Liberties: And
ſelling us into the hands of Tyranny, by which together
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:115732:44"/>
with their other iniquities they have contracted ſo great an
<hi>odium</hi> in the hearts and eyes of all honeſt men, that I know
not whether the hanging up of their Gowns in <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi>
Hall might not be as acceptable a Trophee in the
eyes of the people, as the Scotch Colours.</p>
            <p>I have often wondred, that notwithſtanding the great
miſchief the Nation hath ſuffered by the Lawyers penning
our Laws and Acts of Parliaments, being known to leave
flaws, and alwaies render them ſo lame, they can for their
advantage wreſt them to what ſence they pleaſe, and
thereby make themſelves the Lords and abſolute Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trators
both of our lives and fortunes; that for preventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of like future abuſes they are not excluded the Houſe
of Commons as well as the Clergy, there being as much
reaſon and more precedent for the one then the other,
for that the Judges never had Vote in the Houſe of Peers,
but only ſate upon the Wool-pack, whereas the Biſhops
had like priviledges with the other Lords. It being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
incongruous in reaſon that they ſhould be the makers
of our Laws that are the mercenary Interpreters, leſt byaſt
by their own Intereſts, in ſtead of fences to our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieties,
they make them ſnares to our Lives and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates.</p>
            <p>But it's hoped the prudence of our Senators will
make ſo through a Reformation of the Laws, that as they
are the birthright &amp; inheritance of every Engliſhman, and
the intereſt of all perſons to know and be intimately ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted
with them, ſo they ſhall be rendred ſo facill and
eaſie, that the meaneſt capacity may conceive them, at
leaſt ſo far as he is concern'd therein; that ſo there may
be no longer any occaſion of keeping up ſo corrupt an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt
of men to make juſtice mercenary, who have been
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:115732:44"/>
alwaies found the Panders of Tyranny and betrayers of
our Liberties; and that for the future, every man may
be permitted to be his own Orator and plead his own
cauſe, or procure what friend they pleaſe to be their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates,
that ſo the ſtudy of the Laws may be the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
of our Gentry, who may thereby gain opportunities
of becoming Patriots to the Commons, as were the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<hi>Patricii</hi> to the <hi>Plebeians,</hi> to the begetting a good cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence
between the Gentry and the Commonalty,
and that it may be no longer a mercenary profeſſion of
ſelling Juſtice to the Oppreſſion of the poor, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But that right may be done gratis to every man, and
the cry of the Oppreſſed may no longer be heard in our
Gates; <hi>But that Judgement may run down like a stream,
and Righteouſneſs like a mighty torrent in the midſt of our
ſtreets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall make bold to offer one thing more in reference
to the Law, which is the project that hath been ſo long
diſcourſed of concerning Regiſters in each County, a
project commended by the general ſuffrage of all men,
even Lawyers themſelves as an admiral expedient for
preventing frauds and ſecuring of Inheritances, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
great pitty it is not put in execution, which if it were,
and that all other Courts of Juſtice and Judicature as
ſhall be thought needful for ſecuring the property of the
people, were ſettled in the ſeverall Counties, it would ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
that great and long complain'd of grievance of the
Peoples being conſtrain'd to undergo ſuch ſore and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious
pilgrimages from the fartheſt parts of the Land to
<hi>London.</hi> as if Juſtice had but one Tribunal, or no other
Temple then what is erected in that ſingle City, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence
the whole Nation. I ſhall conclude with that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:115732:45"/>
deſire of the Inhabitants of <hi>Hull</hi> of late, preſented
to the Parliament; <hi>That the Laws by which this Common-wealth
is to be Governed, may be thoſe holy just and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Laws of the great and wiſe God our rightful Lawgiver;
and where any caſe is unprovided for in the expreſs terms of
his word, care may be taken to determine it, with the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act
porportion that is poſsible thereto,</hi> that ſo our Laws be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
founded on the Scriptures, and ſo compos'd, as not
onely to have great affinity with, but alſo to border on
the very ſubburbs of Divinity, the greater Reverence and
Authority may be conciliated to each; and it may ſeem
the leſs incongruous for our Civil Magiſtrate to be <hi>utri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
peritus,</hi> skilful in both.</p>
            <p>Now whatſoever hath been here ſpoken out of a moſt
intenſly heated zeal for publique good, with reflection
on the abuſes of the Law and profeſſors thereof. I would
not have miſconſtrued to reflect upon their perſons which
I honour, and acknowledge many of them to be men
of great Candor and integrity, but rather of the corrupt
intereſt of the profeſſion, it being the deſign of theſe
diſcourſes, to witneſs onely againſt intereſts, and not to
revile or aſperſe the perſons of any whatſoever, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And indeed to ſpeak my mind freely, the grand Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror
in the Reformation of theſe times hath been its weed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
out of perſons, when as the blow ſhould have been
levelled againſt the intereſts, which notwithſtanding the
frequent change of perſons, ſtill take root and ſpring up
in as great vigour as before, and therefore I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,
till the Ax be laid to the root of every evil and
corrupt intereſt, we may not expect to reap any great
fruit or ſucceſs by our Reformation, for all fleſh is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible,
and every man a lie, nor is he that marches in
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:115732:45"/>
the Rear any better able to reſiſt the Temptation, or
avoid the ſnares, then he that fell before him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of the Hereditary Nobility.</head>
            <p>THe Third and laſt ſort of men that ſeem by their
intereſt prompted to an enmity to, and oppoſition
of, an equal Commonwealth, is the Hereditary Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
whoſe apprehenſions being ſwell'd and elated with
the greatneſs of their Titles, and cheriſhing a fond o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion
of the Gallantry of their blood, think it below
them to ſtand on an equall level with the reſt of their
brethren; I confeſs were there on the face of the earth
(according to the fictions of the Poets) a Race of Heroes
that were of the kindred of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and could deduce
their pedigrees from the Gods, whoſe natures had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcap'd
the general pollution, or been leſs tainted with
humane infirmities then other mortals, whoſe bodies had
been fram'd by <hi>Titan,</hi> of better clay, and a more refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
mould then the reſt of the rude Maſs of man kind,
and whoſe parts and intellects (as its ſaid of <hi>Saul</hi>) were
higher by the head and ſhoulders then the reſt of the
peoples, whereby it might be evidenced nature had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned
them unto Rule and Empire: there were then
ſome plea, ſome ground, for that diſtinction the Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
of Cuſtome hath introduc'd among the Children of
men.</p>
            <p>But if theſe Pyramids of greatneſs were at firſt erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ect
by the hands of Monarchy, onely for the better ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
and ornament of the Thrones of Princes, and are,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:115732:46"/>
(if well underſtood) no other then golden Trophies
made of the ſpoiles and ruines of the Peoples Liberties;
that not onely in fair Characters preſerve the memories
of their Oppreſſors, but alſo upbraid them with their
former (if not preſent) ſervitude and ſlavery. I cannot
but think it might much conduce to the ſecurity of the
Peace and Liberty of the Nation, to have them remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
out of the Peoples eyes, that they may neither lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
continue the objects of their Envy who hate them,
or by dazling with their gaudy ſplendor, the weak eyes
o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fond adorers, revive and awaken the memories and
deſires of what they ſometime were the appurtenances
and Appendix: or if they are (as by ſome pretended)
the very pillars and buttreſſes of Monarchy, the Bulworks
and Citadels of Pride and Tyranny, and that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
the ſtandard of Regal Power be taken down,
the Peace and Liberty of the Nation ſeems not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cure, nor to have obtain'd a full and perfect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt
over Oppreſſion, while any of the Fortreſſes in
which it hath formerly been ingariſon'd, be not levelled
and diſmantled; it were better that theſe ſhould abate
ſomething of their Height and grandure, that ſeems to
ore-top and threaten ruine to the publick Liberty: then
that the Nation ſhould be put in danger of relapſing into
ſlavery, or to have their Controverſie ſo lately decided
by the Umpier of Heaven again diſputed in fields of
blood.</p>
            <p>Or if theſe ſwelling Tumours and unhandſome wen
of Greatneſs do ill become the face of a Commonwealth,
and ſpoil the ſymetry and beauty of its proportions; were
it not better they ſhould be pared off, than our
ſtate rendred of a monſtrous and prodigious ſhape? If
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:115732:46"/>
after all our expence of blood and treaſure for purchaſe
of our Liberty, our title and pretenſions to a Free-State
may juſtly be call'd in queſtion, ſo long as we remain
pupils and underwardſhip to our Hereditary Lords and
ancient Guardians, is it not time we were emancipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?
or if that may not in truth be admitted for an equal
Commonwealth, in which there is any other path known
to the Temple of Honour, then what paſſes through
that of virtue? Is it not prudence to hedge up all thoſe
by-wayes of Birth and Fortunes? Were it not better the
ſuſtenance of our polity &amp; Government ſhould be plainly
pen'd without the flouriſhes and Ornaments of ſuch Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitals,
which being admitted, may either ſeem ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
or through miſconſtruction in danger marring of the
ſence, or rendering the nature of our Conſtitution du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious
and ambiguous, than by a contrary practice mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
occaſion of intangling mens judgements with ſuch
ſcruples, knots and difficulties, that the beſt ſtate Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks
being unable to unty, nothing but the ſharpeſt ſword
can cut in ſunder; I would not willingly be underſtood
to plead againſt all diſtinction of Rancks and Degrees
amongſt men, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n which conſiſts the harmony, grace and
beauty of the world, and which cannot be proſcrib'd or
aboliſh'd, without confounding the Oeconomy and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
of all Societies, without unlinking the Chain of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
without cancelling and reverſing the Law of the
univerſe, &amp; un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ovelling the world into its firſt Chaos of
confuſion; Nor ſhould I ſpeak a ſyllable againſt Hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urs
being Hereditary, could the valour, Religion, and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
of Anceſtors be as eaſily intail'd on a line or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily,
as their Honours and Riches, could but their Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry
be made Hereditary as well as their Fortunes?
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:115732:47"/>
Could they tranſmit their vertues as well as names unto
their poſterity, I ſhould willingly become the Advocate
of ſuch a Nobility, and ſuffer my ears to be bored to the
poſts of their doors; and rather acknowledge them our
perpetual Maſters and Dictators, then hazard the choyce
of worſe, upon the doubtful election of the people, with
whom the beſt men are not always in greateſt reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But ſince no choice can be more perillous and unſafe,
then the caſual lot of nature, I had rather ſtand to any
election, then meere chance; by reaſon we have oftner
known fools the ſons of wiſe men by nature, then of the
peoples choice or adoption. Honour is the crown and
reward of Vertue; is it not then unſeemly they ſhould
wear the badge and livery, that were never admitted
within the outmoſt Court of her Temple, that are the
very ſlaves and vaſſals of vice and wickedneſs? I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
but pay a greater tribute of reſpect and honour in my
thoughts, to the worth of ſuch as have raiſed themſelves
to a high degree and pitch of eminence, by the wings
of their own merits, then to ſuch as are onely born up
by thoſe the credit and reputation of their Anceſtors
hath bequeathed unto them: Wherefore that Honour
may be a ſpur to valour, and the reward of Vertue, let
it not be proſtrated to every rich and ſordid miſer, who
by abandoning all Vertue, Hoſpitality and Humanity,
hath with much oppreſſion and grinding the face of the
poor, ſcraped much wealth together; but rather on ſuch
as by their Valour and Prudence, have brought moſt
credit and reputation to the Commonwealth: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
if the Parliament pleaſe out of ſuch to create Knights,
or make the chiefeſt Miniſters of State Lords by Office,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:115732:47"/>
or during life, I ſhould account it no ſoleciſm in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,
but an ornament thereto.</p>
            <p>Now the reaſon I look upon the Divine, the Lawyer,
and Hereditary Nobility, as ſuch irreconcileable Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts
to a Free-ſtate, is not grounded ſingly on the real
prejudice they either have, or are like to receive there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from;
but rather, on what their fears and jealouſies are
apt to ſuggeſt unto their apprehenſions, being conſcious
that their private intereſts ſtand in oppoſition to that of
the Publique; which could they be content to let go, and
wave the advantages an injurious preſcription hath given
them over their Brethren, their concerns would be equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
interwove and wound up with others in that of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth;
and might finde it alike propitious to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
with any other of like parts and ingenuity: But
ſuch is the evil nature of man, that to have done an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury,
is a ſufficient ground for future enmity, and rather
to proſecute, then any way compenſate thoſe that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted
for a former diſcourteſie: Therefore the beſt and
ſooneſt way to be reconciled to ſuch, is quickly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite
their injury; for meaſuring others thirſt of revenge,
by the ſtandard of their own malice, they can never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
any one is friends with them, ſo long as he is in ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears
to them for an ill turn: So that their fear of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge
breeds diſtance, and that encreaſes alienation and
diſaffection, which brings forth farther hoſtility, with
encreaſe of injuries. In Analogy to which Doctrine,
the beſt way to give the Antagoniſts of the Common-wealth
eaſe, and its ſelf ſecurity, is, by cauſing their
fears to fall upon them, and thereby deliver them from
further pain, and the Publike from its jealouſies and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
danger; for it can never be expected, they ſhould
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:115732:48"/>
eſpouſe the intereſt of the Publique, before they have
buried that of their private; that they ſhould imbark
themſelves in the ſame bottom with that of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,
ſo long as they have ſo many of their own
to look after; till theſe are ſhipwrack'd, they will not
be much concerned in the ſafety and proſperity of the
Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>We ſhall never be ſo well united in our affections and
deſigns for publick good, as when we are become all
of one price, and to have but one common intereſt: for
it is nothing but the diverſity of Intereſts that breaks us
in pieces, and crumbles us into ſo many different facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
and deſigns, which as it was good policy in our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>chs,
ſo but bad prudence in a Commonwealth: the
Intereſt of a Prince being to break the ſtrength of his
people, that one faction being ballanc'd by another, he
may with more eaſe and facility render himſelfe Maſter
of all, according to the advice of the old Maxime, <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide
and Rule.</hi> But the ſtrength and glory of a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth
is its union. And indeed it had otherwiſe been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible,
that ever Princes ſhould have been able to
have tyed up the hands of Nations, and bound the
ſtrength of <hi>Sampſon</hi> in Cords, and bands of withyes;
had not the policy like that of the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> firſt ſhorn
their locks, and deprived them of their ſtrength: Had
they not firſt according to the fable of the Faggot, loos'd
their bond of union, by ſtarting many intereſts, and
kindling divers animoſities among them, they had never
faſtned the Cords of ſlavery and bondage on them.
The <hi>Philiſtims</hi> had never ſported themſelves with <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi>
or <hi>Uliſſes</hi> with <hi>Polyphemas,</hi> had they not firſt put out
their eyes. Nor had <hi>Princes</hi> ever put a hook into the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:115732:48"/>
of the Leviathan, or plaid with the mighty Whale;
had they not made uſe of a like ſtratagem.</p>
            <p>Men complain much, and ſeem to have a great ſenſe
of the many Factions and Diviſions in Religion, as they
are pleaſed to term them; but how inconſiderable are
theſe to the grand National or civil Factions. I confeſs
thoſe of Religion may ſometime be made uſe of to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liate,
but they are of other factions, that are the bitter root
of all our breaches and diviſions: Were there not one
intereſt of the Nobility, another of the Commonalty;
one of the Clergy, another of the Laity; one of the
Lawyer, another of the Countryman; one of the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier,
another of the Citizen; one of the elder, another of
the younger Brethren, we might ſoon ſee an end of the
other.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the intereſt that claſh ſo much one againſt
another, and make ſuch tumults in the world; and were
theſe once cancelled and forgotten, the other of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian
and Independent, Quaker and Anabaptiſt, &amp;c.
would ſoon vaniſh, or at leaſt, make little noiſe or diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance
in the world. How happy might all men be, did
it pleaſe God they might recover the fight of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
intereſt, and their ſtrength which conſiſts in union.
How eaſily might all the Nations of the earth ſhake off
the iron Yokes the Tyranny of Princes hath put upon
them by this means? and with how great facility might
this be done! with how little prejudice and detriment to
any mans particular, might all be made happy, if lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
aſide all animoſities and jealouſies, men would but
lend an ear to reaſon, rather then paſſion. But to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed,
ſince it hath pleaſed God once more to put a price
into our hands, and cauſe another opportunity of reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:115732:49"/>
our Native Rights and Liberties to dawn upon us,
I deſire we may not be as fools, not knowing how to uſe
it; but that all ways that are ſafe and honourable may be
taken for the ſecuring and improvement of it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
that the builders of our State may be furniſhed with
a ſpirit of Wiſdom from above, that they may become
<hi>The Repairers of our Breaches,</hi> and, <hi>The Reſtorers of
Pathes to dwell in;</hi> that they may not deceive themſelves,
or the Nation, by thinking to patch up a ſorry half potch'd
Commonwealth, upon the old, crazy, and rotten foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations
of Monarchy as heretofore; having had expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience,
that it will not, it cannot ſtand. They that are
beſt read in Politicks, and have b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en moſt converſant in
the Hiſtories of antiquity, know, that as a Commonwealth
is the beſt and moſt abſolute form of Government; ſo it
is a nice and tickliſh thing, and hath been difficult to fix
in Nations under leſs diſadvantage then we, vvho have
been ſo long uſed to a contrary vvay of Government:
which I ſpeak not to diſcourage, but rather awaken the
endeavours and reſolutions of our Senators, to watch
and ſecure our liberties. The ancient Commonwealths
have been neceſſitated to make uſe ſometimes of violent
phyſick, to purge and evacuate the rank humours of the
Body Politick, and ſuch as I would not have preſcribed
a Chriſtian State, ſuppoſing there may be found out ſuch
as are more ſafe and gentle. It was the unhappineſs of
the Grecian and Roman Republique, to be o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ten guilty
of the greateſt ingratitude towards them that beſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
of them; and not unoften to ſtain their hands with
their bloods, whoſe former merits ſeemed to challenge a
Crown, rather then a Croſs from them. How often
hath <hi>Greece,</hi> for the ſecurity of her liberty, ſacrificed
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:115732:49"/>
that life, by which ſhe hath formerly been preſerved from
ruine and deſtruction? Who hath not heard of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy
Tragedy of that valiant Captain, that more then
once preſerved the Capitol, and ſnatched <hi>Rome,</hi> as a prey,
out of the very teeth of the <hi>Galls,</hi> its barbarous, and at
laſt fatal enemies? And how often hath <hi>Greece</hi> rewarded
her Captains victories with Baniſhment, inſtead of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph?
and that upon the ſingle account of ſome ſmall
ſuggeſtion of jealouſie, or weak argument of too great
Magnificence or Popularity: ſo jealous were thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publiques
of their liberty, that the General of an Army
durſt not make uſe of a little Plate in his Houſe, leaſt it
ſhould cauſe envy, or render him ſuſpected of too much
Grandure and Ambition, and that he endeavoured to
ſupplant the Commonwealth, and render himſelf their
Lord and Maſter. Others have been conſtrained to le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel
their Palaces with the ground, leſt the ſumptuouſneſs
and magnificence of their Structure, ſhould become the
object of the Peoples envy and hatred. When theſe
things come into my minde, I cannot but wonder any
ſhould think it ſo eaſie and facile a thing to erect a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,
as that it may be done with a wet finger, and
requires no more then inſerting, <hi>The Keepers of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties,</hi>
inſtead of the name <hi>King,</hi> and that then the work
is finiſhed, without any farther trouble or alteration, as
many ſeem to be of opinion. I confeſs, had we not at
ſo dear a rate bought experience to inform us of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,
this miſtake might have paſt for venial, but that
makes it an unpardonable errour. Now what may (as I
humbly conceive) have a conſiderable influence on the
Nation, for the better fixing it on the right baſis of a
Free-State, are as followeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:115732:50"/>
            <head>Of an Agrarian.</head>
            <p>1. FIrſt, that there may be an Agrarian fixed, for
ſtinting and ſetting bounds to the vaſt unſatiable
deſires that are found in greedy men after riches; which
makes them not onely lay field to field, and joyn houſe
to houſe (as was the complaint of the old Prophets) but
to lay Town to Town, Pariſh to Pariſh, County to
County, and Iſland to Iſland. May we ever expect a
more righteous adminiſtration of things, while there are
no bounds ſet to the waves of this raging paſſion, that is
ready to ſwallow, not onely the houſes of the widow,
but whole Countreys? while there is no check upon co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs,
the root of all evils; upon the immoderate
deſires of men, that like the daughters of the Horſleach,
cry, <hi>Give, give;</hi> that are more unſatiable then Hell, or
the Grave. Shall a price be ſet on the poor mans ſweat
and labour, and ſhall the growth of families have no
bound? ſhall they raiſe their houſes (according to the
deſign of <hi>Babel</hi>) to the Heavens? as if having filled the
earth with oppreſſion, they would take Heaven alſo by
violence. Is this ſuitable to a Commonwealth? or was
this the deſign of our Reformation, to put the whole Land
into the hands of a few Proprietors? was it for this end
Abbeys were demoliſhed, &amp; the Hierarchy taken down,
that a few Gentlemen, or elder Brethren, might have
their lands, becauſe they had not enough before? Is this
the purchaſe of all our blood and treaſure? to ſet up a
few more gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at families, to encreaſe the number of our
Maſters; who when they have ingroſſed the lands and
wealth of the whole Nation, there will remain nothing
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:115732:50"/>
for either of them to purchaſe, or us to ſell, but our ſelves
to be their ſlaves, and ſo reſtore vaſſallage, that hath
been ſo long abrogated. We have had great diſputes
and ſharp controverſies; firſt, about a Houſe of Lords,
and ſince a Senate: But, in my apprehenſion, not worth
a bulruſh; for the caſe is the ſame, whether Lords or not
Lords, when as the great Landlords in each Country,
ſhall be conſtantly choſen by their Tenants, to be our Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlators.
Were it not as good they ſhould have patents
to ſit for life, ſince we cannot ſuppoſe they will willingly
accept of a Writ of Eaſe, or ſit out of play (having to
great ſtakes in the game) ſo long as they can ſo eaſily be
ſhouldered in by their Tenants: Or if at any time they be
kept out, have we not experience that they will leavy
war againſt the preſent power? Doth not the war at this
preſent day witneſs thereto? is it not then all one, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
we have an everlaſting <hi>Parliament,</hi> or ſucceſſive, if
elections are but a new choice of the ſame men, and that
it be not difficult to prick a <hi>Parliament,</hi> before the Writs
are gone forth? And were this all the inconvenience, the
evil were more tolerable; but do we not ſee how apt theſe
Gentlemen of ſuch vaſt and rank Eſtates are to leavy
war, and imbrue the Land in blood? doth not this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
from the greatneſs of their retinue, the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
of their tenants, the aſfluency of their eſtates and
fortunes?</p>
            <p>Now what better expedient can be deviſed for this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief
then an Agrarian? is it not more juſt and equira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
then the Grecian oſtraciſm, or the Roman proſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?
can a Commonwealth be fixed without it? is it not
abſolutely neceſſary, that the proportion of lands be ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
leſt otherw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e the whole Iſland in proceſs of time fall
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:115732:51"/>
into the hands of one or few <hi>Proprietors?</hi> what then will
become of our Free-ſtate? will not our Landlords erect
what Government they pleaſe over us? moreover, will
not this give great encouragement to hoſpitality, &amp; works
of charity, that men ſhould know the bounds of their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates,
the pillars on which is wrote their <hi>ne plus ultra?</hi> how
can we ever expect good laws, or a more righteous State,
while thoſe worms of the earth, that poſſeſs the greateſt
dunghills, muſt be our Senators, becauſe they have the
greateſt rout of tenants to voyce them into the ſaddle of
Authority. Is this ſuitable to a Free-State, or becoming
Chriſtians? To what purpoſe is more wealth then what
may with credit bear up the port of a chief Miniſter of
State, and furniſh forth the comforts and enjoyments of
this life? is not he a Leviathan, and more greedy then
Death, Hell, or the grave, that deſires more? Now that
ſuch an Agrarian (which for its proportion, is ſubmitted
to the wiſdom of our Senators) may be introduc'd, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
breaking down the hedge of any mans propriety, it is
humbly propoſed, that there may be a time aſſigned,
wherein they that want poſterity, or a noble ſpirit to part
with any of their wealth to their poor relations, may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert
their lands into a perſonal eſtate, or otherwiſe diſpoſe
of them, by reaſon that an exceſs or redundancy in that,
as expoſed to greater caſualty and hazard, ſo is of leſs dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
to the Commonwealth then the other, which time ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired,
that all taxes &amp; publike charges may be laid on ſuch
as have not conformed thereto, til their eſtates be crumbled
down to the common ſtandard, or due proportion, &amp; that
the State or Commonwealth may be declared heir, and to
inherit whatever beyond the juſt proportion of the fixed
Agrarian any man ſhall leave unto his heir or poſterity.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:115732:51"/>
            <head>Of the Militia.</head>
            <p>2. THat at all thoſe that have been true to, and by the
free expence of their bloud and treaſure, have
purchaſed a ſhare and intereſt in the cauſe God, hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
to crown with ſo great ſucceſs and victory, may be
put in poſture to defend their Liberties, and trained up to
the uſe of Arms and Military Diſcipline, in all places
throughout the Land, untill time ſhall have worn out all
animoſities, and that the whole Nation ſhall become in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely
united in their affections one to another, and be as
of one lump, and then that all may be exerciſed in Arms
that are not uncapable either through age or infirmity. I
need not I preſume ſhew how commendable a thing
it is for a Nation to be of a couragious and martiall ſpirit,
or how neceſſary they ſhould bear their own Arms, and
not to put weapons into the hands of ſtrangers, or their
ſlaves to make them their Maſters, and become ſubject to
a baſe and mercenary Army, being things ſo clear, that
he that hath but halt an eye may reade and foreſee their
inconveniences.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of Elections to Offices, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>3. THat certain fundamental Conſtitutions, by which
both the ſpiritual and civil Liberties of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
may be ſecured, be agreed on, and all that expect the
priviledge of vote or ſuffrage in Elect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons of Knights of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:115732:52"/>
the Shires, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or to bear any office of truſt in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth
may be ſworn thereto, and that men may be
eſteemed qualified, not ſo much by their eſtates, as Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
and Virtue of bearing the chief offices of truſt in the
Commonwealth; and to this end that the qualifications
according to which they are to be capacitated, may be
ſo ſtated and limited, as to bear the acceſs of all unworthy
perſons that are like to betray their truſt, or connive at
the ſpringings up of Uſurpations, Tyranny and Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;
and by reaſon the Elections of Parliament men are
at preſent managed with ſo much tumult and noiſe, that
the more ſober and modeſt people are aſhamed, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged
to be preſent at them: that the Parliament
would think of ſome other way by Subſcriptions in each
Pariſh, or the like, leſs ſubject to popular tumults, in
which the more rude and violent carry it from the more
diſcreet and ſober, not ſo much by plurality of voices as
by noiſe and violence, being (as commonly managed)
more like an Aſſembly met, to chooſe the Lord of a
Whitſun-Ale, then Knights of the Shire. As alſo that
none may be truſted with more power then God hath fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
them with a capacity to underſtand, and abilities
to adminiſter without ſtain to the reputation of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth;
and therefore that no Apes in purple, or
Aſſes with golden Trappings, may be admitted to ſit and
bray upon our Tribunals and Seats of judicature, to bring
Authority into contempt and diſgrace: But that every
one may carry their own brains, and not underſtand their
Places by Proxy, or have the Orbs and Sphears of their
underſtandings turned about and governed by a mercena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
intelligence, as is the Cuſtome of ſome Reverend
Mayors by their Learned Recorders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:115732:52"/>
I confeſs here to fore for the encouragement of Trade,
there might be ſome Reaſon of endowing Corporations
with large priviledges, but ſince all Trades have been o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſtock'd,
the caſe is much altered. It might alſo be
more the intereſt of Princes, to truſt a good ſhare of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
in the hands of ſheepiſh and tame Citizens, that are
content not only to pay dearer for their honour, but alſo
depend more upon their will and humour then thoſe that
better underſtand themſelves: Whereas the intereſt of a
Commonwealth is to employ ſuch as are leſs flegmatick
and more mercuriall, of greater ſpirit, prudence and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctivity
for the management of their ſeveral Truſts and
Provinces, then are uſually found among ſuch as have
had the advantage of no better Education then their
Trades; or known other Academy then their Shops or
Exchange.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Of Rotation.</head>
            <p>LAſtly, That there may be ſuch an equal Rotation of
all Offices of Truſt and Places of power, that all that
are capable may alike taſte of Rule as well as ſubjection:
By reaſon that fixed powers, like ſtanding waters, are apt
to corrupt and ſtink in the Noſtrils of the people.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:115732:53"/>
            <head>The Concluſion.</head>
            <p>MAny other things might have been propoſed, but
not knowing what Reception will be given, to what
hath already been ſaid, I ſhall at preſent for bear. I have
not preſumed to chalk out any particular modell, refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
that to the wiſedom of our Senators, that are beſt
able to determine thereof: And were they pleaſed to
borrow light from any others apprehenſions, there are
not wanting, whoſe thoughts and Pens having been well
traverſed on that Subject, may better expect that honour
then I; My deſigne being only to propoſe ſome Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental
things, that may lay a firm Baſis for an equal
Common-wealth to be founded on, leaving the form and
ſuperſtructure thereof to be erected by the hands of our
Maſter-builders, which through the bleſſing of God have
never miſcarried in any of their Heroick Undertakings.</p>
            <p>And whatever others may think of the deſigne of theſe
diſcourſes, I am ſo well ſatisfied in my own breaſt, that
I think I may be bold to ſay, it is that God hath ſignally
owned, and what his people, the good people of this
Land, are by a ſpirit of faith ſtrongly carried forth in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation
of. Certainly ſuch a Common-wealth as is
here pleaded for, is the beſt and moſt happy of all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments,
is the beſt and moſt religious of all Cauſes;
and whatever of Religion is pleaded againſt it, is either of
ignorance or malice; for what detriment can this bring
to Religion? Is it becauſe a mercenary Miniſtry is more
holy, more acceptable, then one that is free? or to
preach for hire be better then out of zeal and conſcience?
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:115732:53"/>
or is a Clergy taken from the meaneſt of the people, more
holy, more righteous then the heads and Princes thereof?
Is not the firſt-born as acceptable as the younger Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren?
How then may a Common-wealth be charged
with ſupplantiug Religion or deſtroying Piety? Doth
that ſubvert either Magiſtracy or Miniſtry, that twiſts
them both together: Many would fain have their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
Biſhops, and their Biſhops Lords, Is it not as well
if our Lords be Biſhops? Many would have the Clergy
encreaſed, and Miniſters made Juſtices of Peace, Is it
not as well if our Juſtices of Peace become Miniſters?
Let it not therefore be ſaid, that through the ſides of the
Miniſtry we would wound Magiſtracy, when it's deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
they ſhould be a ſupport and ornament to each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>But may our Government more truly be accuſed of
diſcouraging Learning? May that be thought guilty of
this, that prefers every man according to his deſerts? that
by the Rotation of its offices, takes in every one to have
his ſhare, and turn in the adminiſtration of its power?
That furniſhes every man with employment ſutable to
the greatneſs of his parts and Education, that ſuffers no
mans Talent to ruſt, to lie hid, to be buried or laid up in
a Napkin, but invites and gives opportunity for the uſe
and exerciſe of them. Is to contract the number of Hals
and Colledges (when the Nation is over-ſtock'd) to
diſcourage Learning? Did not my Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> long ſince
complain thereof, when there were fewer Colledges and
more preferments? and is there not more reaſon now? I
preſume no body will ſay that Learned <hi>Heroe</hi> was an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy
of Learning. Is it rationall to think theſe times
need as many Colledges as thoſe before <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. when
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:115732:54"/>
there were thirty thouſand Students in one of the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities;
And yet that we may not envy thoſe times, little
the more learning; for doth not every one know what
Scholars the Monks were? And how learned thoſe Ages
that ſwarmed with ſo many fat and flow bellies? Did not
one of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings tranſlate the Bible for the uſe of
his illiterate Clergy, becauſe his Clergy underſtood not
Latine as he gives the Reaſon? And do we not now
ſpoil many a good Plough-man to make a poor Scholar,
and rob the Shops of many a fit mechanick, to keep
our Colledges thinly ſtock'd with half-witted ſleepiſh
Fellows?</p>
            <p>And is this for the Advancement of Learning, to
render it more common and contemptible then the Art
of Fidling? That the education and exerciſe of Princes
ſhould become the ſtudy of every pedant and peſant;
That <hi>Minerva</hi> and the Muſes ſhould be proſtrated to the
prophane accoſts of every <hi>Coridon,</hi> and ſullied by the
rude embraces of every Mechanick Son? Is it not that
too hath brought it into ſo much contempt and diſgrace
with the Gentry and Nobility? that hath made it accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
a baſe and pedantick thing? Is not Learning cheap e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough,
when greater Parts and Ingenuity may be hired
for a peece of bread, then would heretofore have purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
a Cardinals Hat? Should we make enquiry into the
Cauſes of that detriment Learning hath received, and
what obſtructs the Advancement thereof, we ſhould
finde it another thing then what moſt men ſuppoſe. It
is that diſtinction and diverſity of modern times have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced,
whence have ſprung many nice and curious
ſtudies unknown to Antiquity, and the wiſer ages of the
world, ſtudies that bring no advantage to the Common-wealth,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:115732:54"/>
that yeeld neither pleaſure nor profit to thoſe
that converſe in them, ſave what folly and cuſtome
hath intail'd upon them, ſtudies in which our choiceſt
wits do loſe their time, and conſume their ſtrength to
no purpoſe; except to become skillfull in a literate
kinde of ignorance, while the more ſolid parts of
Learning lie altogether uncultivated and neglected:
Studies that are not only jejune and barren of any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable
Fruit, but ſuch as ſophiſticate and adulterate
the underſtandings of all thoſe that are moſt conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
in them; That preoccupy and blurre the minde
with prejudice, and render men froward and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe
to the reception of the Truth; Studies that
blinde the Underſtanding, deprave the Will, byaſſe
the Judgement and corrupt the affections; That ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
men moroſe, peeviſh, uncharitable and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane:
That crowd the world with multitudes of
Books, of which there is no end, either in reſpect of
number, or their uſe, ſuch as might better be ſpared
then read, and if burnt, the world neither the leſs
wiſe nor learned; For demonſtration of which I ſhall
inſtance in two or three profeſſions of great repute in
the world, and firſt of Divines which are commonly
diſtinguiſhed into Caſuiſts Polemick School, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall
Divines; Of which all or the moſt part might
very well have been ſpared, had men acquieſced in
the Scriptures, and been content to have waited on
the Teachings of Gods Spirit: But ſo ſoon as the
wiſedom of men, and Policy of Princes had erected
this which ſhould be all mens ſtudy and employment
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:115732:55"/>
into a particular Profeſſion, and regiſtred it among
thoſe that are commonly called the Learned; To adde
the more credit thereto, they began to mix and blend
it with the Learning and Sophiſtry of the Schools, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending
to adorn-it with the ſpoils of the Heathen, but
what is found to have ſophiſticated and adulterated the
truth and ſimplicity of the Goſpel: Now becauſe
this mixing it with falſe and incoherent School-Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
had (through its incongruity and contradiction)
brought forth great variety and multiplicity of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
and in all probability ſpawn'd moſt of thoſe
Sects, Hereſies, and Errours, that now ſwarme and
are lodged in the Heads and Judgements of unſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
mindes: It was thought neceſſary to introduce
Polemicks for purging and winnowing Divinity
from the Chaffe of ſuch Errours, as the former pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice
had filled it with; and therefore certain Colled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
were erected for Students of Controverſies, for
maintaining the <hi>Gideons</hi> and Champions of the Truth,
who like the Knights Templers, or thoſe of <hi>Malta</hi> were
to defend the Holy Land, or maintain the poſſeſſions
of Truth, from the invaſions and incroachings of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,
which was performed with ſuch ill ſucceſs, that
in ſtead of compoſing and reducing errours to the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience
of the Truth, they became much multiplyed
by the ſubtle cavilling wits of theſe perſons altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
given to wrangling and contradiction, that at
length the very Fundamentals of Religion came to be
called in Queſtion, and the Pillars of faith ſhaken,
and all things rendred diſputable, and argued <hi>pro</hi> and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:115732:55"/>
               <hi>con,</hi> by the perverſe and ſcepticall wits of Truths
pretended Champions. Thus rather then they would
ſeem idle or want employment, they fell to ſeeking
knots in Bull-ruſhes, and made, where they could not
finde difficulties, till at length the itch of diſputing
proved the ſcab of the Church, while in the mean
time all neceſſary and uſefull Learning was neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected.</p>
            <p>By the like ſteps and degrees did the ſtudy of the
Laws alſo climbe into the repute of a Learned Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion:
For firſt, Monarchy having introduced a great
variety of tenures, reſulting from the diverſity of feuds
and ſervices, as Grand Sergeanty, Knight-Service,
Soccage, and the like. which are but ſo many ſeverall
degrees of ſervitude and ſlavery, their ſtudy was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated
to a peculiar order of men, who to render
their profeſſion more difficult and advantagious, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced
the prolix tautological forms of Inſtruments
that are in uſe at this day, that through the multitude
of words they might darken knowledge, though under
a contrary pretence of perſpicuity and avoiding ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guity;
and being intruſted with penning of Acts, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances
and Statutes, they rendred them dubious and
ambiguous for the better grounding contrary caſes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
them, to which time hath added multitudes of read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
on Statutes, Comments corrupting and darkening
the Text, Reports, Caſes, Abridgements, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by
which the Law is rendred ſo intricate, prolix, and ſcab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed,
that it racks and tortures the beſt wits that have
undertaken the ſtudy thereof. Now there is no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:115732:56"/>
badge of the ſlavery of any people then the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
of their Laws, it being their intereſt to have them
as few, brief, and plain as poſſible, and to ſpeak truth,
Law is or ought to be nothing but pure Reaſon found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
on the Word of God, or ſuch clear and naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences
and deductions as unbyaſt reaſon ſhall make
from the Morall Law, and then what need would there
be of thoſe many Books and large Volumes of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Reports, Caſes, Preſidents, Comments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with
which the world is crouded.</p>
            <p>I might in like manner inſtance in Politicks, which
as commonly handled, is nothing but an Art of knave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
that conſiſts in ballancing of Factions, and caſting a
miſt of different intereſts before the eyes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
making them ſcramble for Nuts and Trifles, or
like the dog in the Fable, catch at ſpecious ſhadows,
while they let go the ſubſtance, and ſuffer themſelves
to be cajol'd and jugled out of their Liberties, and
made a prey to exorbitant and arbitrary power; of
which (were the eyes of men open to diſcern their true
and common intereſt, which is to aboliſh all names of
diſtinction and faction) there would be no uſe, for
honeſty would be found the moſt genuine and true po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy,
and that which would abide the touch, when all
other ſhall be found falſe and counterfeit: When the
credit of all our Quacks and Empericks of King-craft
and State-policy ſhall become Bankrupt, and they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
like Mountebanks to remove their Stages and
ſeek new Quarters, wherein to ſet up their Trade of
Jugling: How many of theſe have we of late ſeen
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:115732:56"/>
with diſgrace hiſt off the Stage, before they had well
look'd about them! how many of theſe crafty Foxes
have of late been unkenell'd, and their faces covered
with ſhame, that they have been glad to hide themſelves
in corners: Thoſe (that like the Foxes of <hi>Sampſon</hi> with
firebrands in their tales) were ſo skilful in kindling facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
and jealouſies, to ſet the world on fire; as if, like
<hi>Nero,</hi> they were with nothing ſo wel pleaſed, as to warm
themſelves at the ruines of the world. Now were all
theſe ſpurious excreſcencies prun'd from the Tree of
Knowledge, theſe curious, uſeleſs and pernitious ſtudies
abrogated, theſe mazes and meanders of trifles (in which
moſt of our beſt wits are loſt and wilder'd) removed:
How would all thoſe pathes that lead to uſeful know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
that are now unfrequented and over grown with
weeds, be reſorted to? How would all the fruitful parts
of learning be cultivated? what profitable voyages might
be made to the <hi>America</hi> &amp; remoteſt parts of nature, that
are yet unknown and undiſcovered? what admirable
ſcholars, and how able and learned a Gentry might we
then expect to ſee, that had acquired not onely a ſmall
ſmattering in a little curious and uſeleſs learning, and
made a ſmall progreſs in ſome one of the learned profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
but had run through them all; that were not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Lawyers, but alſo Divines, Stateſmen, Hiſtorians,
Philoſophers, Phyſicians, in a word, not lame (as now<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adays)
but abſolute and univerſal ſcholars: This is the
true account of learnings decays and detriment, with the
readieſt means of reſtoring it to its <hi>Priſtine</hi> ſtrength and
luſtre, to which I knovv nothing that hath greater ten-dency
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:115732:57"/>
then the Commonvvealth propoſed, ſo far it
is from being prejudicial thereto.</p>
            <p>To proceed therefore, have then the Lawyers any
juſt cauſe to criminate our Government, or to bring
in a large bill of Indictment againſt it, or implead it as
guilty of injury to them? is it any wrong to them for
every one to plead his own cauſe? have they any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt
or propriety in other mens cauſes, in the Suits
and Contentions of other men? if not, wherein are
they injured? in that every one is preſumed to tell his
own tale beſt, to be moſt eloquent in his own behalf,
and to beſt underſtand his own buſineſs? is it not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
to be wondred, that the Gentry and Nobility
have with patience ſo long ſuffered themſelves to be
ſlighted, contemned and trampled on, by a Mercenary
Generation of men, that ſell their breath, as Laplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
do winds, and raiſe and enrich themſelves by the
ruines and ſhipwracks of others fortunes?</p>
            <p>Or in the laſt place, will the Nobility ſuffer any
great loſs hereby? is there any thing more then a gild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
title, a bare and empty name that is in jeopardy,
which in a Commonwealth either ſignifies nothing, or
what amounts not to ſo much as a feather in their caps?
or if they are loth to part with it, may they not wear
it to their graves? No body deſires that any of the
preſent Proprietors ſhould be robbed of one <hi>Iota</hi> in their
titles; and I preſume none will deſire them any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
If they do, <hi>Lucian</hi> will tell them they are mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken,
their Honours muſt not wait on them to the
other world, they muſt not enter with them into <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:115732:57"/>
Boat, the ſurly Ferriman will have them left on
this ſide the banks of <hi>Acheron.</hi> But if they deſire
they ſhould deſcend to their poſterity, if ſo be their
eſtates be equally divided according to Gavel-kinde,
we ſhall not much differ about that, if one or all of
their ſons (according to the cuſtom of ſome Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys)
aſſume the titles of their Anceſtors, I know
none will envy their Honours, or be much of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended
with their petty Lordſhips; onely I ſhould
think it more generous and prudent to lay them down
at the Commonwealths feet; and after they ſhall have
approved themſelves perſons of Worth, Honour,
and Integrity to their Countrey, they need not doubt
but to receive them with greater luſtre and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,
as a badge rather of their own then their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors
Vertues. If now the partition walls (as hath
been propoſed) of all particular and private inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts
(at firſt erected by the ſubtilty of Princes)
were thus broken down, and the intereſt of every
particular become the intereſt of all, and the intereſt
of all but one; how happy, how unanimous ſhould
we be? and how plain and eaſie a thing would the
Doctrine of Politicks become? with how great eaſe
and facility might the Helme of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth
be ſteered and governed? in how great peace
and tranquility ſhould we live? what a conſtant ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renity
of Peace and Proſperity might we enjoy?
We might then beat our Swords into Plow-ſhares,
and turn our Spears into Pruning-Hooks, we ſhould
then no more hear the ſound of the Drum, or be
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:115732:58"/>
affrighted vvith the Alarums of Civil Wars and
diſcords; but might ſit under our own Vines, and
eat the fruit of our Figge-trees in ſafety: We ſhould
then ſee the Wolf dwell with the Lamb, and the
Leopard lie down with the Kid, and the Calf, and
the young Lyon, and the Fatling together, and a
little Childe to lead them, and The Lyon ſhall
eat ſtraw like an Ox, and the Sucking Childe ſhall
play upon the hole of the Aſp, and the weaned
Childe ſhall put his hand upon the Cockatrice Den;
for they ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy throughout the
Holy Mountain of the Lord: But the vvhole
Earth ſhall be full of the Knowledge of the Lord, as
the waters cover the Sea.</p>
            <p>Thus ſhall it be, when the Knowledge of the
Lord hath deſtroyed every baſe and private Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
from off the face of the Earth; when he hath
taken away that diverſity of Preying Intereſts, that
are the Source and Spring of all our miſeries, the
ſeeds of all thoſe Factions and Diviſions that rage
among the ſons of Men, and makes them tear,
rend, and prey upon one another, that hath ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled
the Doctrine of Politicks, and rendred
them ſo dark and abſtruce, a Labyrinth ſo difficult,
a Maze and Myſterie of Iniquity, that hath turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
the Art of Government, into an Art of Jugling
and diſſembling; that hath brought to light thoſe
wicked Machavilian Maximes of the Kingdome of
Darkneſſe, that were firſt broached by a Conclave
of Devils, <hi>Divide &amp; impera: Qui neſcit diſsimulare
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:115732:58"/>
neſcit regnare,</hi> and the like; that hath deviſed neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity
of State as an Apologie, and Religious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences
as a cloak for the blackeſt crimes the Sunne
ere looked upon; that hath put the Inſcription of
the Cauſe of God, upon moſt wicked and Devil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
Deſigns; that hath made Religion hold the ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup
to Ambition, become the Pander of Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
and a Stalking-Horſe to Luſt and Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.
But it ſhall not be thus in the Holy Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
of the Lord, in the Holy Commonwealth of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> that is coming down
from above, and when there ſhall be new Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,
and new Earth, all old things ſhall paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,
which is not far off; the World, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe
of man hath now but a ſhort part to
act; for the time is approaching, in which every
falſe Mask and Vizard ſhall be pulled off, in
which a window ſhall be opened into every ſecret
and falſe breaſt, and the hidden thoughts of mens
hearts diſcovered; and that the World ſhall be no
longer cheated, to eſpouſe corrupt and baſe Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts,
becauſe gilded with glorious pretences of
Religion, and bearing Falſe Inſcriptions upon
them.</p>
            <p>Now for the truth and reaſon of theſe things, I
durſt appeal to the Iudgements and Conſciences of
the moſt underſtanding men in the Nation, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
their hearts witneſſe to them; and were their
bodies of Chryſtal, pellucid, and tranſparent, I
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:115732:59"/>
know we might read the ſame Apprehenſions in
them: for I cannot imagine it proceeds from ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance,
but intereſt, that the light of thoſe truths
hath not hitherto been more diſcovered. So many
are intereſſed in the grand Cheat of the World,
ſo many are the Silverſmiths that reap profit from
the Shrines of theſe <hi>Diana</hi>'s, that it is no wonder
there appears ſo great a zeal to keep up their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit
and reputation: But the day of the Lord which
is at hand, will diſcover them. I know moſt men
are led by a blinde and implicite faith they have
pinned on the ſleeves of ſome learned Rabbies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
ready to Worſhip and fall down before any
Galf, Cuſtom hath ſet up among them: Theſe out
of love I have endeavoured to undeceive, though
I thereby ſet up my ſelf as a Mark and But for
all the ſhafts the Malice of men can dart againſt
me. And being loth to detain and impriſon the
Truth in unrighteouſneſſe, have given in my teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
againſt the Corruption of the World, which
I know to be a cheat; and the manners of men,
who are a lye, and Vanity. How it will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived,
I am not ſolicitous; if I periſh, I periſh,
and hope I ſhall be able to ſay, as ſometime that
Great Souldier <hi>Beliſarius, Mihi non culpa nocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it
ſed invidia.</hi> But as for the Truth, I know
it cannot long be ſtifled, but muſt and will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Magna eſt veritas &amp; praevalebit.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:115732:59"/>
            <head>THE
CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>A</hi> Plea for a Commonwealth, page 1.</item>
               <item>Of the Miniſtry or Clergy, page 21</item>
               <item>Of Tythes, page 38</item>
               <item>An humble Motion in behalf of the Poor, page 42</item>
               <item>Of the Univerſities, page 45</item>
               <item>Of the Regulation of the Laws and Lawyers, page 56</item>
               <item>An Apology for Younger Brothers, page 58</item>
               <item>Of the Hereditary Nobility, page 75</item>
               <item>Of an Agrarian, page 84</item>
               <item>Of the Militia, page 87</item>
               <item>Of Election to Offices, <hi>&amp;c. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Rotation. page 89</item>
               <item>The Concluſion. page 90</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
